<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Selection on Silje Synnøve Lyder Hermansen</title>
    <link>/tags/selection/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Selection on Silje Synnøve Lyder Hermansen</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 01 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	    <atom:link href="/tags/selection/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Delegation of committee reports in the European Parliament</title>
      <link>/publication/eup2020/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/publication/eup2020/</guid>
      <description>&lt;!---
&lt;a href=&#34;&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;EffectOfSpecialization.png&#34; alt=&#34;The positive effect of staying in the same committee decreases over time.&#34;&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;
---&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Abstract&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Committee coordinators face a classic delegation problem when assigning reports to their committee members. Although few theoretical developments have focused on the eﬀects of expertise on delegation, empirical studies have commonly assumed monotonic eﬀects. Based on the theoretical model by Fischer and Stocken (2001), we argue that more expertise, holding preference divergence constant, has a non-monotonic eﬀect on the probability of being appointed as a rapporteur because of informational credibility. Employing accumulated committee service as an expertise measure, we test this theoretical expectation on all committee report delegations in the European Parliament from 1979 - 2014. Across both nonparametric and parametric hierarchical conditional logit models we ﬁnd support for this non-monotonic eﬀect. The results hold across member states, political groups, procedures, committees, and over time.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!---
**Replication files** can be downloaded [here](https://github.com/SiljeHermansen/Replication-files)
---&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Reference&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Chiou, Fang-Yi, Hermansen, Silje Synnøve Lyder and Bjørn Høyland (2020) &amp;ldquo;Delegation of Committee Reports in the European Parliament&amp;rdquo; &lt;em&gt;European Union Politics&lt;/em&gt; 21(2), 1-19.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Choosing Agents: Members of the European Parliament and their Political Organizations Seen through Report Allocation</title>
      <link>/publication/phd2017/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 10 Mar 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/publication/phd2017/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.duo.uio.no/bitstream/handle/10852/69004/PhD-LyderHermansen-2017.pdf?sequence=4&amp;isAllowed=y&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;committee_activity.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Graphic illustrating the variation in committee activity in the European Parliament (1999-2014). Author: Silje Synnøve Lyder Hermansen&#34;&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Abstract&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This dissertation treats with partisan organization in the European Parliament (EP) and its impact on members’ (MEPs) career opportunities. National parties organize elections. Parliamentary work is organized around transnational political groups. They do not share any overarching organizational structure. My contributions pertain to the interconnected choices made by MEPs and their two party organizations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Parliamentary groups face a trade-off between the need for expertise and the risk of agency drift. Groups allocate reports to maximize the value added by the rapporteur while limiting the drift. They prefer policy experts to generalists and -- up to a point -- experienced MEPs to newcomers. Groups also balance individual demands with the collective need.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;National parties do not have institutionalized presence in the EP. They enter into an outcome-based contract similar to voters. MEPs are either rewarded by reselection or kicked out of office. Report alloca-tions dissipate uncertainty about MEPs’ ability. They thus improve MEPs’ career prospects to the extent that parties need new information about agent quality, and to the extent that parliamentary groups can provide it.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
