<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Silje Synnøve Lyder Hermansen</title>
    <link>/authors/pegan/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Silje Synnøve Lyder Hermansen</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 01 Feb 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	    <atom:link href="/authors/pegan/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Blurred lines between electoral and parliamentary representation: The use of constituency staff among Members of the European Parliament</title>
      <link>/publication/eup2023/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Feb 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/publication/eup2023/</guid>
      <description>&lt;!---
&lt;a href=&#34;&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;EffectOfSpecialization.png&#34; alt=&#34;The positive effect of staying in the same committee decreases over time.&#34;&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;
---&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Abstract&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Parliamentarians receive public funding to employ staff in the constituency helping them execute their representative mandate. However, local staff is also an electoral asset. We draw on theories of personal-vote seeking to study local staff as an example of constituency service. Modelling within-individual changes in local-staff size among 1174 Members of the European Parliament (MEPs), we find that staff size increases before both European and national elections and more so in candidate-centred systems. This leads us to conclude that - despite a single staff system for all MEPs - EU citizens are represented differently depending on where they elect their members. The attempt to mend EU&#39;s democratic deficit by financing members&#39; contact with citizens further implies funding incumbent European candidates and challengers in national campaigns.&lt;/p&gt; 
&lt;!---
**Replication files** can be downloaded [here](https://github.com/SiljeHermansen/Replication-files)
---&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Reference&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Hermansen, Silje Synnøve Lyder and Andreja Pegan (2023) &amp;ldquo;Blurred lines between electoral and parliamentary representation: The use of constituency staff among Members of the European Parliament&amp;rdquo; &lt;em&gt;European Union Politics&lt;/em&gt;, 24 (2), pp 239–263.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
