<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Silje Synnøve Lyder Hermansen</title>
    <link>/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Silje Synnøve Lyder Hermansen</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 01 Sep 2019 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	    <atom:link href="/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Lær deg R</title>
      <link>/data/laerdegr_bok/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Sep 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/data/laerdegr_bok/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.fagbokforlaget.no/L%C3%A6r-deg-R/I9788245022131&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;laerdegr.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Lær deg R: En innføring i statistikkprogrammets muligheter. Forfatter: Silje Synnøve Lyder Hermansen&#34;&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Abstract&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt; Velkommen til R-universet! Lær deg R er introduksjonen for deg som ønsker et godt arbeidsverktøy for statistisk analyse.  R har vokst enormt i popularitet de siste årene, og med god grunn. R er gratis og dekker analysebehovene til nybegynnere så vel som eksperter.&lt;/p&gt;  
    &lt;p&gt;Boka er skrevet for samfunnsviteren som tar sine første skritt innen kvantitativ metode. Statistikk er et håndverk mer enn en vitenskap. Derfor er verktøyet viktig. Vi jobber sammen i RStudio, og går gjennom analysestadiene skritt for skritt. Vi laster inn data, tilrettelegger dem, gjør foranalyser og regresjonsanalyser. Fokuset er på å forstå hva som skjer, og kommunisere resultatene.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Boka er levert med datasett, øvelsesoppgaver og løsningsforslag, slik at du kan prøve deg på egen hånd. Alt du trenger er en datamaskin, internett og denne boka.&lt;/p&gt;
  

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Lær deg R-pakken&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lær deg R-pakken er en nettressurs som gir deg tilgang til datasett og oppgaveløsninger som hører til boka. Du kan laste ned pakken som .tar.gz-fil eller som .zip-fil:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/SiljeHermansen/laerdegR/raw/master/laerdegR_0.1.0.tar.gz&#34; download&gt;
&lt;button class=&#34;button&#34;&gt;&lt;i class=&#34;fa fa-download&#34;&gt;&lt;/i&gt; laerdegR_0.1.0.tar.gz&lt;/button&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/SiljeHermansen/laerdegR/raw/master/laerdegR_0.1.0.zip&#34; download&gt;
&lt;button class=&#34;button&#34;&gt;&lt;i class=&#34;fa fa-download&#34;&gt;&lt;/i&gt; laerdegR_0.1.0.zip&lt;/button&gt;
&lt;/a&gt; 
&lt;/div&gt;
 

&lt;p&gt;Instrukser om hvordan du installerer pakken finner du på denne siden:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://siljehermansen.github.io/data/laerdegr&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Last ned og installere laerdegR&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Innholdsfortegnelse&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Boka tar deg skritt for skritt gjennom en typisk forskningsprosess.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Vi begynner med å laste inn og tilrettelegge data, før vi går videre med beskrivende analyser. I siste del av boka kjører vi så regresjonsanalyser: OLS og logistisk regresjon. Vi har fokus på å forstå og tolke resultatene. Dette inkluderer også å vurdere modellens troverdighet gjennom ulike former for modellstatistikk.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;embed src=&#34;Innholdsfortegnelse.pdf&#34; width=&#34;700&#34; height=&#34;950&#34; alt=&#34;Innholdsfortegnelse til Lær deg R&#34; pluginspage=&#34;http://www.adobe.com/products/acrobat/readstep2.html&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Decision makers in the Court of Justice of the European Union (CJEU)</title>
      <link>/project/court-of-justice-of-the-european-union/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Aug 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/project/court-of-justice-of-the-european-union/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;The Court of Justice of the European Union (CJEU) has established itself as the world’s most influential international court, functioning in many respects as a federal supreme court.  This project aims to better understand the conditions for -– and therefore the limits of -– the Court’s independence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I open the black box of the decision-making process to consider governments’ and judges’ individual behavior. As of today, very little research exists on how judges enter the Court and how its internal organization affect decision-making.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!---## [Case allocation within the Court](case-allocation)---&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;case-allocation-within-the-court&#34;&gt;Case allocation within the Court&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;!---* &lt;a href=&#34;TendingTheBar_Hermansen.pdf&#34; style=&#34;color: #000000&#34;&gt;**&#34;Tending the Bar: Strategic Case Allocations in
the Court of Justice of the European Union&#34;**&lt;/a&gt;   presented at EPSA Annual Meeting 2019 (Belfast)---&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&amp;ldquo;Tending the Bar: Strategic Case Allocations in the Court of Justice of the European Union&amp;rdquo;&lt;/strong&gt; presented at EPSA Annual Meeting 2019 (Belfast)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Does the President of the Court of Justice of the European Union (CJEU) make strategic use of his members? To date, studies in the separation-of-powers tradition have considered the Court’s behavior at the organizational level. In contrast, this paper focuses on the effect of external strategic considerations on allocation of influence within the Court.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Contrary to many other international courts, influence in the CJEU is individualized and distributed at the discretion of its leadership. First, I show that the President promotes individual-level specialization and argue that this favors consistency in the Court’s output. Second, I argue that suspicions about judges’ political accountability can polarize already politicized cases. The President shortcuts such dynamics by allocating cases to judges whose governments occupy a moderate position.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I rely on original data on allocations in 9955 cases brought before the CJEU (1980-2015). The results speak to the role of internal organization for judicial independence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;MarginalEffect_First_B_item_Current_government_-_weighted0.jpeg&#34; width=&#34;50%&#34; align=&#34;left&#34; alt=&#34;No effect of government preferences in non-politicized cases.&#34;/&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;MarginalEffect_First_B_item_Current_government_-_weighted1.jpeg&#34; width=&#34;50%&#34; align=&#34;right&#34; alt=&#34;Effect of government preferences in politicized cases.&#34;/&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Judges whose governments hold outlying economic preferences are less likely to act as rapporteur in court cases that could divide member states.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A draft version can be found &lt;a href=&#34;TendingTheBar_Hermansen.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;appointment-of-judges&#34;&gt;Appointment of judges&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&amp;ldquo;Will do? Selecting Judges on the Basis of Policy Preferences or Performance Indicators&amp;rdquo;&lt;/strong&gt;  with Daniel Naurin presented at the ECPR Joint Sessions 2019 (Mons)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;!---* &lt;a href=&#34;WillDo_HermansenNaurin.pdf&#34; style=&#34;color: #000000&#34;&gt;**&#34;Will do? Selecting Judges on the Basis of Policy Preferences or Performance Indicators&#34;**&lt;/a&gt;  with Daniel Naurin presented at the ECPR Joint Sessions 2019 (Mons)---&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Are governments’ appointments of judges to the Court of Justice of the European Union (CJEU) politicized? And does this prevent them for emphasizing competence? The power to select judges is key to representative institutions’ control over the judiciary. Nevertheless, while the CJEU is the most powerful of international courts and motor of the judicialization of politics in Europe, the selection criteria that governments follow have remained a blank in the literature.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Judges in the CJEU sit for six years renewable. All cases are decided collectively and in secrecy, so the policies judges favor are unknown. However, their influence &amp;ndash; in terms of the positions they obtain –&amp;ndash; is known. We therefore start by assuming that judges are selected for their preferences, but sanctioned for their performance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;Effect_of_preferences_on_change_of_judge.jpeg&#34; width=&#34;50%&#34; align=&#34;right&#34; alt=&#34;The likelihood of replacing a sitting judge increases with the distance between the economic preferences of the appointing and reappointing government.&#34;/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We rely on original data on all potential reappointment decisions to the CJEU over a 60-year period, biographical information and key performance measures of judges’ activities at the Court.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We find on the one hand that governments with different economic preferences hold different preferences over judges. That is, a change in government preferences increases the likelihood of changing the sitting judge. On the other hand, we find that governments &amp;ndash; regardless of their political preferences &amp;ndash; are more likely to retain judges who have obtained positions of influence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A draft version can be found &lt;a href=&#34;WillDo_HermansenNaurin.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!---
## Data collection on decision makers
The internal organization of the Court has become both more complex and more hierarchical over time.
![The internal organization of the Court has become both more complex and more hierarchical over time.](Timeline.gif)
---&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Decision makers in the European Parliament (EP)</title>
      <link>/project/european-parliament/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Aug 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/project/european-parliament/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;!---
&lt;img src=&#34;EP.jpg&#34; align=&#34;centre&#34;, caption = &#34;The European Parliament in Strasbourg&#34;/&gt;
---&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Party organizations obtain influence through their choice of representatives. Extra-parliamentary party organizations gain sway through the candidates for whom they secure election, while parliamentary party groups shape policies through the allocation of tasks to competent members. This project delves into the mutual influence of parliamentary group allocations and the choices made by extra-parliamentary party organizations. In the center are members of Parliament whose political careers are shaped by both actors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;electoral-behavior&#34;&gt;Electoral behavior&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;National parties do not have institutionalized presence in the EP. They enter
into an outcome-based contract similar to voters. MEPs are either rewarded by reselection or kicked out of office. Report allocations dissipate uncertainty about MEPs’ ability. They thus improve MEPs’ career prospects to the extent that parties need new information about agent quality, and to the extent that parliamentary groups can provide it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;ongoing-work&#34;&gt;Ongoing work&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&amp;ldquo;The sanction that isn’t imposed? Roll-call voting loyalty and demotion in European Parliament elections&amp;rdquo;&lt;/strong&gt; with &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.researchgate.net/profile/Mihail_Chiru&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Mihail Chiru&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.researchgate.net/profile/Thomas_Daeubler&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Thomas Däubler&lt;/a&gt;, presented at EPSA Annual Meeting 2019 (Belfast)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This article introduces a comprehensive data collection effortthat provides detailed election results, list ranking information, seat and vote attributes for MEPs, EP candidates and parties covering four electoral periods and legislative terms, from 1999 until the 2014 elections. The described data will facilitate a broad spectrum of empirical analyses of the EP, thus helping to improve our understanding of this unique parliamentary body. Possible applications include studies of the EP&amp;rsquo;s allegedly weak electoral connection, of whether personalized electoral systems make any difference with respect to whom is elected in the EP, or whether electoral rules mediate MEPs&amp;rsquo; career ambitions. The article illustratesthe main features of the datasets and their usefulness with brief analyses of intra-party competition in EP elections, the degree of usage of preference votes and its consequences, and the effects of voting disloyalty in the subsequent re-nomination process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&amp;ldquo;Blurred Lines: The Use of Constituency-Based Assistants among Election-Seekers&amp;rdquo;&lt;/strong&gt; with &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.pegan.org/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Andreja Pegan&lt;/a&gt;, presented at EPSA Annual Meeting 2017 (Vienna)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Do parliamentarians use their staff allowances for (re)election purposes? If so, what electoral institutions mediate that investment? We argue that local staff (&amp;ldquo;constituency staff&amp;rdquo;) is used to promote candidacies. Candidates must persuade two actors whose importance varies according to the electoral system: their party or voters. Thus, we expect that parliamentarians&amp;rsquo; investment in local staff is a function of their political ambition and the electoral system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To test the argument, we study the number of constituency hires by 1174 individual Members of the European Parliament (MEPs) over a five-year period. We find that the size follows European and national electoral cycles. Members from candidate-centered systems keep more local assistants on their pay roll, and are more responsive to the electoral calendar. In party-centered systems, reelection-seeking members also invest more locally than those who wish to exit Parliament, but the investment is lower and fluctuates less than in candidate-centered systems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A draft version can be found &lt;a href=&#34;BlurredLines.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&amp;ldquo;How Do Legislated Gender Quotas Impact Representation?&amp;rdquo;&lt;/strong&gt; Working paper presented at EPSA Annual Meeting 2016 (Brussels)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How does biased political recruitment – and the subsequent legislation of quotas
– affect the quality of women’s performance as representatives in Parliament?
I draw on insights from the literature on political agency to distinguish between
the effects of selection and sanction.  First, if recruitment in the absence of quotas implies higher requirements for women, then selected women are of higher quality. Second, when quotas lower the bar, new women enter office.  However, parties are less certain about the quality of these women and react by increasing accountability.
I investigate representation in the European Parliament (1999-2014) before and
after the legislation of quotas in several member states.  Absent quotas, I find that biased selection leads to female representatives who pursue longer careers and perform better at equal levels of effort.  When quotas are legislated, parties emphasize women’s service records during reselection.  Women are thus incentivized to put in more effort.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A draft version can be found &lt;a href=&#34;Gender.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A popularized presentation (in Norwegian) can be found &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.sv.uio.no/isv/forskning/aktuelt/aktuelle-saker/2017/et-forsvar-for-kvinnekvotering-.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;published-work&#34;&gt;Published work&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;/publication/pp2018/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Striving for influence: The effect of performance on candidate selection&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt; (2018) &lt;em&gt;Party Politics&lt;/em&gt; 24 (4), 382-396.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;legislative-behavior&#34;&gt;Legislative behavior&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The European Parliament (EP) is a committee-oriented legislature; meaning that the bulk of legislative work is done in committees.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Parliamentary groups face a trade-off between the need for expertise and the risk of agency drift. Groups allocate reports to maximize the value added by the rapporteur while limiting the drift. They prefer policy experts to generalists and &amp;ndash; up to a point &amp;ndash; experienced MEPs to newcomers. Groups also balance individual demands with the collective need.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;ongoing-projects&#34;&gt;Ongoing projects&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&amp;ldquo;Delegation of Committee Reports in the European Parliament&amp;rdquo;&lt;/strong&gt; with &lt;a href=&#34;http://idv.sinica.edu.tw/fchiou/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Fang-Yi Chiou&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://bjornhoyland.github.io/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Bjørn Høyland&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Committee coordinators face a classic delegation problem when assigning re-
ports to their committee members. Although few theoretical developments have
focused on the effects of expertise on delegation, empirical studies have commonly
assumed monotonic effects. Based on the theoretical model by Fischer and Stocken
(2001), we argue that more expertise, holding preference divergence constant, has
a non-monotonic effect on the probability of being appointed as a rapporteur be-
cause of informational credibility. Employing accumulated committee service as
an expertise measure, we test this theoretical expectation on all committee report
delegations in the European Parliament from 1979 - 2014. Across both nonparametric and parametric hierarchical conditional logit models we find support for this non-monotonic effect. The results hold across member states, political groups,
procedures, committees, and over time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;published-work-1&#34;&gt;Published work&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;!---
* [&#34;(Self-)selection and expertise among decision-makers in the European Parliament&#34;] ( /publication/jls2018/) (2018) *The Journal of Legislative Studies*.
[ ](Selfselection.pdf)
---&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;Selfselection.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;&amp;rdquo;(Self-)selection and expertise among decision-makers in the European Parliament&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt; (2018) &lt;em&gt;The Journal of Legislative Studies&lt;/em&gt; 24 (1), 148-172.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.duo.uio.no/bitstream/handle/10852/69004/PhD-LyderHermansen-2017.pdf?sequence=4&amp;amp;isAllowed=y&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Choosing Agents: Members of the European Parliament and their Political Organizations Seen through Report Allocation&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt; (2017) Doctoral dissertation, &lt;em&gt;University of Oslo&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Installere R-pakken</title>
      <link>/data/laerdegr/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Aug 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/data/laerdegr/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.fagbokforlaget.no/L%C3%A6r-deg-R/I9788245022131&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Lær deg R&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt; er en innføringsbok i statistikkprogrammet R utgitt av Fagbokforlaget (2019). Boka er levert med datasett, øvelsesoppgaver og løsningsforslag, slik at du kan prøve deg på egen hånd. Her kan du laste ned denne nettressursen. Den kommer som en egen R-pakke.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pakken kan installeres fra lokal fil eller rett fra GitHub.
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.fagbokforlaget.no/L%C3%A6r-deg-R/I9788245022131&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;laerdegr.jpg&#34; width=&#34;35%&#34; align=&#34;right&#34; alt=&#34;Lær deg R: En innføring i statistikkprogrammets muligheter. Forfatter: Silje Synnøve Lyder Hermansen&#34;&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;installere-fra-lokal-fil&#34;&gt;Installere fra lokal fil&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Denne løsningen gjøres i to skritt.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;På denne siden&lt;/strong&gt; laster du ned pakken ved å trykke på én av disse lenkene:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For alle operativsystemer:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/SiljeHermansen/laerdegR/raw/master/laerdegR_0.1.0.tar.gz&#34; download&gt;
&lt;button class=&#34;button&#34;&gt;&lt;i class=&#34;fa fa-download&#34;&gt;&lt;/i&gt; laerdegR_0.1.0.tar.gz&lt;/button&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Windows-brukere kan også benytte seg av denne:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/SiljeHermansen/laerdegR/raw/master/laerdegR_0.1.0.zip&#34; download&gt;
&lt;button class=&#34;button&#34;&gt;&lt;i class=&#34;fa fa-download&#34;&gt;&lt;/i&gt; laerdegR_0.1.0.zip&lt;/button&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Filen vil da lastes ned på din maskin. Om du ikke har spesifisert annet, vil den ligge i mappen som kalles &amp;ldquo;Downloads&amp;rdquo; på maskinen din.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;I RStudio&lt;/strong&gt; installerer du filen i R-biblioteket.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Klikk på fanen som kalles &amp;ldquo;Packages&amp;rdquo; i vinduet nederst til høyre.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Klikk så på &amp;ldquo;Install&amp;rdquo;. I kommunikasjonsvinduet som så åpner seg, skal du velge &amp;ldquo;Install from: Package Archive File&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Under &amp;ldquo;Package archive:&amp;rdquo; må du deretter klikke på &amp;ldquo;Browse&amp;rdquo; og navigere deg fram til filen du nettopp lastet ned.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Klikk så på &amp;ldquo;Install&amp;rdquo;. Nå skrives installasjonskommandoen til R, og R skal i rask rekkefølge gi deg beskjed i rød skrift om at pakken installeres, og i svart skrift at &lt;code&gt;package ‘laerdegR’ successfully unpacked and MD5 sums checked&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Om møter på feilmeldinger, bør du sjekke at tilleggsargumentene i installasjonskoden er korrekte. Filadressa (&lt;code&gt;C:/Downloads/&lt;/code&gt;) vil åpenbart variere fra maskin til maskin.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Om du har valgt tar.gz-fil, må koden se slik ut.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;install.packages(&amp;quot;C:/Downloads/laerdegR_0.1.0.tar.gz&amp;quot;, repos = NULL, type = &amp;quot;source&amp;quot;)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Om du har valgt zip-fil, må koden se slik ut.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;install.packages(&amp;quot;C:/Downloads/laerdegR_0.1.0.zip&amp;quot;, repos = NULL, type = &amp;quot;binary&amp;quot;)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;installere-direkte-fra-github&#34;&gt;Installere direkte fra GitHub&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Denne løsningen krever mer manøvrering.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;I nettleseren:&lt;/strong&gt; Begynn med å laste ned og installere &lt;a href=&#34;https://cran.r-project.org/bin/windows/Rtools/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;RTools&lt;/a&gt; uten å åpne RStudio.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;I RStudio:&lt;/strong&gt; installere &lt;code&gt;devtools&lt;/code&gt;-pakken og hent den inn fra biblioteket.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;install.packages(&#39;devtools&#39;)
library(devtools)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nå kan du laste ned og installere nettressursen direkte fra GitHubs sider.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;install_github(&amp;quot;SiljeHermansen/laerdegR&amp;quot;)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Lær deg R</title>
      <link>/publication/laerdegr/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Aug 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/publication/laerdegr/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.fagbokforlaget.no/L%C3%A6r-deg-R/I9788245022131&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;laerdegr.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Lær deg R: En innføring i statistikkprogrammets muligheter. Forfatter: Silje Synnøve Lyder Hermansen&#34;&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Abstract&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt; Velkommen til R-universet! Lær deg R er introduksjonen for deg som ønsker et godt arbeidsverktøy for statistisk analyse.  R har vokst enormt i popularitet de siste årene, og med god grunn. R er gratis og dekker analysebehovene til nybegynnere så vel som eksperter.&lt;/p&gt;  
    &lt;p&gt;Boka er skrevet for samfunnsviteren som tar sine første skritt innen kvantitativ metode. Statistikk er et håndverk mer enn en vitenskap. Derfor er verktøyet viktig. Vi jobber sammen i RStudio, og går gjennom analysestadiene skritt for skritt. Vi laster inn data, tilrettelegger dem, gjør foranalyser og regresjonsanalyser. Fokuset er på å forstå hva som skjer, og kommunisere resultatene.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Boka er levert med datasett, øvelsesoppgaver og løsningsforslag, slik at du kan prøve deg på egen hånd. Alt du trenger er en datamaskin, internett og denne boka.&lt;/p&gt;
  

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Lær deg R-pakken&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lær deg R-pakken er en nettressurs som gir deg tilgang til datasett og oppgaveløsninger som hører til boka. Du kan laste ned pakken som .tar.gz-fil eller som .zip-fil:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/SiljeHermansen/laerdegR/raw/master/laerdegR_0.1.0.tar.gz&#34; download&gt;
&lt;button class=&#34;button&#34;&gt;&lt;i class=&#34;fa fa-download&#34;&gt;&lt;/i&gt; laerdegR_0.1.0.tar.gz&lt;/button&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/SiljeHermansen/laerdegR/raw/master/laerdegR_0.1.0.zip&#34; download&gt;
&lt;button class=&#34;button&#34;&gt;&lt;i class=&#34;fa fa-download&#34;&gt;&lt;/i&gt; laerdegR_0.1.0.zip&lt;/button&gt;
&lt;/a&gt; 
&lt;/div&gt;
 

&lt;p&gt;Instrukser om hvordan du installerer pakken finner du på denne siden:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://siljehermansen.github.io/data/laerdegr&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Last ned og installere laerdegR&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Innholdsfortegnelse&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Boka tar deg skritt for skritt gjennom en typisk forskningsprosess.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Vi begynner med å laste inn og tilrettelegge data, før vi går videre med beskrivende analyser. I siste del av boka kjører vi så regresjonsanalyser: OLS og logistisk regresjon. Vi har fokus på å forstå og tolke resultatene. Dette inkluderer også å vurdere modellens troverdighet gjennom ulike former for modellstatistikk.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;embed src=&#34;Innholdsfortegnelse.pdf&#34; width=&#34;700&#34; height=&#34;950&#34; alt=&#34;Innholdsfortegnelse til Lær deg R&#34; pluginspage=&#34;http://www.adobe.com/products/acrobat/readstep2.html&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Striving for influence: The effect of performance on candidate selection</title>
      <link>/publication/pp2018/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Jul 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/publication/pp2018/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://journals.sagepub.com/doi/full/10.1177/1354068816663036&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;reselection_performance.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Effect of signals of performance on incumbent candidate selection to the European Parliament. Author: Silje Hermansen.&#34;&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Abstract&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I consider how asymmetric information between the party selectorate and members of Parliament affects the renomination of incumbent candidates. By applying an adverse selection model, I argue that the selectorate looks to past performance to select candidates it expects will gain influence. However, the impact of performance varies according to the need for and availability of information.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The European Parliament (EP) provides a most-likely case for information asymmetry. Studying three elections in 11 member states, I find that the allocation of influential positions in office improves chances of reselection. The effect increases when the allocation is more selective, and when the prior uncertainty around candidacies is high. The study thus proposes a new approach to the relationship between national parties and transnational groups in the EP. It also suggests venues for research on parliamentary politics and candidate selection in general. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Replication files&lt;/strong&gt; can be downloaded &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/SiljeHermansen/Replication-files&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Privacy Policy</title>
      <link>/privacy/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 28 Jun 2018 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/privacy/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>(Self-)selection and expertise among decision-makers in the European Parliament</title>
      <link>/publication/jls2018/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 16 Mar 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/publication/jls2018/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.tandfonline.com/doi/full/10.1080/13572334.2018.1444631&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;coefplot_expertise.png&#34; alt=&#34;Coefplot reporting effect of policy expertise on allocation of codecision reports. Author: Silje Hermansen.&#34;&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Abstract&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rapporteurs in the European Parliament (EP) are the most influential members in terms of the legislation they handle. They are appointed by their political groups. In making these appointments, these groups need to accommodate both their collective needs and individual requests.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This article explores situations in which the collective need for information is prioritised: the codecision procedure. The data includes allocations over a 10-year period (2004–2014) in three of the most powerful EP committees, as well as key career choices among members.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;EP groups emphasise policy-specific expertise. They also pay attention to individual members’ requests for exposure, but only when the expected policy drift is minimal. Harsh selection during the allocation of codecision reports creates pressure to accommodate a greater selection of legislators during other attractive report allocations. Own-initiative reports therefore affect allocation of codecision reports negatively.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Online supplementary files&lt;/strong&gt; can be downloaded &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/SiljeHermansen/Replication-files&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Choosing Agents: Members of the European Parliament and their Political Organizations Seen through Report Allocation</title>
      <link>/publication/phd2017/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 10 Mar 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/publication/phd2017/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.duo.uio.no/bitstream/handle/10852/69004/PhD-LyderHermansen-2017.pdf?sequence=4&amp;isAllowed=y&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;committee_activity.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Graphic illustrating the variation in committee activity in the European Parliament (1999-2014). Author: Silje Synnøve Lyder Hermansen&#34;&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Abstract&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This dissertation treats with partisan organization in the European Parliament (EP) and its impact on members’ (MEPs) career opportunities. National parties organize elections. Parliamentary work is organized around transnational political groups. They do not share any overarching organizational structure. My contributions pertain to the interconnected choices made by MEPs and their two party organizations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Parliamentary groups face a trade-off between the need for expertise and the risk of agency drift. Groups allocate reports to maximize the value added by the rapporteur while limiting the drift. They prefer policy experts to generalists and -- up to a point -- experienced MEPs to newcomers. Groups also balance individual demands with the collective need.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;National parties do not have institutionalized presence in the EP. They enter into an outcome-based contract similar to voters. MEPs are either rewarded by reselection or kicked out of office. Report alloca-tions dissipate uncertainty about MEPs’ ability. They thus improve MEPs’ career prospects to the extent that parties need new information about agent quality, and to the extent that parliamentary groups can provide it.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
