<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Teaching material on Silje Synnøve Lyder Hermansen</title>
    <link>https://siljehermansen.github.io/tags/teaching-material/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Teaching material on Silje Synnøve Lyder Hermansen</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 26 Nov 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	    <atom:link href="https://siljehermansen.github.io/tags/teaching-material/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>What GLM should I choose?</title>
      <link>https://siljehermansen.github.io/teaching/choose_glm/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 26 Nov 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://siljehermansen.github.io/teaching/choose_glm/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;How can I choose the best (parsimonious) description of my data? Here is my mental map of choice criteria when I consider what Generalized Linear Model (GLM) to rely on.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let&#39;s assume I want to describe the relationship (&amp;beta;) between an independent variable (&lt;em&gt;x&lt;/em&gt;) and a dependent variable (&lt;em&gt;y&lt;/em&gt;) in the form of:
&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;math display = &#34;block&#34;&gt;
      y = &amp;alpha; + &amp;beta;x + &amp;epsilon;
    &lt;/math&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let&#39;s furthermore assume that the ideal description is not only parsimonious (i.e. it suffices with one parameter &amp;beta;) but also faithful to the data (i.e. the model predicts outcomes consistently over the entire range of &lt;em&gt;y&lt;/em&gt;). GLMs come in handy when we want to describe relationships in which the distribution of errors (&amp;epsilon;) is not normal.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;html&gt;
&lt;head&gt;&lt;title&gt;Decision tree for GLMs&lt;/title&gt;&lt;/head&gt;
&lt;body&gt;
&lt;iframe id=&#34;decision tree for glms app&#34; src=&#34;model_choice.html&#34; style=&#34;border: none; width: 100%; height: 1250px&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/body&gt;
&lt;/html&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I generally begin by considering how my dependent variable is measured and the data generating process that I believe produced it. It is standard procedure to check if the assumptions inherent in the model are satisfied and potentially reconsider the choice.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Statistical analysis (STV4020B)</title>
      <link>https://siljehermansen.github.io/teaching/stv4020b/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Nov 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://siljehermansen.github.io/teaching/stv4020b/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Master&amp;rsquo;s/PhD level. &lt;em&gt;University of Oslo. Department of Political Science.&lt;/em&gt; 2020&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!---Here you can find the slides and other material used for the different lectures.---&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This course provides a toolkit for students looking to execute their own research projects using quantitative methods. We explain the statistical theory behind models, but we emphasize understanding when different models are useful and how to employ them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The course helps students 1) identify appropriate statistical models that describe different data types and 2) design studies that enable causal inference (as opposed to merely establishing correlation).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;describing-data-generalized-linear-models&#34;&gt;Describing data (generalized linear models)&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many of the phenomena political scientists take interest in can be classified into categories or events. This includes variables like voters&#39; choice of party, number of violent incidences in a time span, or time between violent events. The course introduces students to a number of models which are specifically designed to describe the underlying phenomenon that generates such data. The focus of the first part of the course is on correlations. Our purpose is to help students gear the statistical analysis towards a realistic description of the data.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;lecture-1-maximum-likelihood&#34;&gt;Lecture 1: Maximum likelihood&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;(Ward and Ahlquist, 2018, ch 1, 2, 5-7)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We introduce maximum likelihood as a framework for statistical modeling.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;lecture-2-models-of-outcome-and-choice-the-logit-modellogit_model_stv4020bpdf&#34;&gt;Lecture 2: &lt;a href=&#34;logit_model_stv4020b.pdf&#34;&gt;Models of outcome and choice: The logit model&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;(Ward and Ahlquist, 2018, ch 3)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Logistic regression is the base-line example of a generalized linear model (GLM).
We go through how to model binary outcomes, how to interpret the results from a logit and why we can&amp;rsquo;t simply run an OLS.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;lecture-3-models-of-outcome-and-choice-ordered-and-multinomial-regressionchoice_models_stv4020bpdf&#34;&gt;Lecture 3: &lt;a href=&#34;choice_models_stv4020b.pdf&#34;&gt;Models of outcome and choice: Ordered and multinomial regression&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;(Ward and Ahlquist, 2018, ch 8-9)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We go through models with categorical dependent variables: Ordinal and nominal categories. Example data used in class can be downloaded &lt;a href=&#34;kap10.txt&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. It is the same as the data from chapter 10 in laerdegR.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;lecture-4-event-count-models-poisson-regression-and-other-alternativescount_models_stv4020bpdf&#34;&gt;Lecture 4: &lt;a href=&#34;count_models_stv4020b.pdf&#34;&gt;Event count models: Poisson regression and other alternatives&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;(Ward and Ahlquist, 2018, ch 10)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Event count models describe grouped events. They are appropriate when we do not have relevant information at the event level, but are able to both count them and design contextual predictors. We go through the poisson model and how to check for overdispersion. We then consider different strategies to adress possible overdispersion. We study the quasi-poisson and the negative binomial models as well as hurle and zero-inflated models.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Towards the end of the lecture, we consider the &lt;a href=&#34;https://siljehermansen.github.io/teaching/choose_glm&#34;&gt;decision tree for determining which GLM model&lt;/a&gt; might best describe our data.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;lecture-5-event-historyduration-models&#34;&gt;Lecture 5: Event history/duration models&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;(Ward and Ahlquist, 2018, ch 11)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We can leverage information both from the fact that an event occured or not (binary outcome) and the time it took for the event to take place (count outcome). These models are made to describe a duration until an outcome occurs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;causal-inference&#34;&gt;Causal inference&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Beyond statistical description, researchers&#39; interest in political phenomena is often motivated by a wish to identify their causes. Causal claims focus on whether we would continue to observe $y$ even in the absence of $x$. This is a typical question when studying the effect of policies, for example. The potential outcomes framework helps us understand the conditions under which we can identify causal relationships.  The second part of the course is devoted to a set of quantitative research designs that can be used to make causal inferences.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;causal-inferencecausal_inference_stv4020bpdf&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;causal_inference_stv4020b.pdf&#34;&gt;Causal inference&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;(Morgan and Winship, 2015, ch 1-3; Samii 2016)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We go through the idea of potential outcomes. What are the comparisons we would we like to make? And what is actually possible to compare with?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the R-lab we&amp;rsquo;ll look at matching techniques. We will play with a version of the &lt;a href=&#34;judges.rda&#34;&gt;data&lt;/a&gt; from Glyn and Sen&amp;rsquo;s daughters-effect paper in &lt;a href=&#34;https://scholar.harvard.edu/files/msen/files/daughters.pdf&#34;&gt;APSR&lt;/a&gt; from 2014.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;regression-and-matching&#34;&gt;Regression and matching&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;(Ho et al., 2007; Iacus, King and Porro, 2011)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We introduce matching as a technique to adjust for observed confounders.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;rdd-and-diff-in-diffrdd_diff-in-diff_stv4020bpdf&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;RDD_diff-in-diff_stv4020b.pdf&#34;&gt;RDD and diff-in-diff&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;(Angrist and Pischke, 2015, ch 4 and 5; Wing, Simon and Bello-Gomez, 2018; Imbens and Lemieux 2008)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We go through regression discontinuity designs (RDD) where a treatment kicks in at a certain cutpoint of an observed running variable. We then have a look at the differences-in-differences approach (diff-in-diff) where we observe a treatment group and a control group before and after the treatment. It&amp;rsquo;s all about interaction effects and dummies!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We&amp;rsquo;ll play around with data on young adults, deathrates and alcohol both from &lt;a href=&#34;df_ch4.rda&#34;&gt;chapter 4&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;df_ch5.rda&#34;&gt;chapter 5&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;instrumental-variables&#34;&gt;Instrumental variables&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;(Sovey and Green, 2011)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We introduce instrumental variables and provide guidelines for their application in political science.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;complete-syllabus&#34;&gt;Complete syllabus&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div&gt;
&lt;object data=&#34;syllabus_stv4020b.pdf&#34; type=&#34;application/pdf&#34; width=&#34;700&#34; height=&#34;950&#34;&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;syllabus_stv4020b.pdf&#34;&gt;Download the syllabus for Statistical analysis (stv4020b)&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/object&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Learning outcome&lt;/strong&gt;  Students will get hands-on practice by learning how to implement the various techniques and by replicating existing studies in R. Students will also learn how to present results in a manner that is understandable to a general audience, for example by using graphs and other visual tools.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;More information&lt;/strong&gt; about the course is available at the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.uio.no/studier/emner/sv/statsvitenskap/STV4020B/&#34;&gt;University of Oslo&amp;rsquo;s webpages&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!---
### Course description 
This course provides a toolkit for students looking to execute their own research projects using quantitative methods. We explain the statistical theory behind models, but we emphasize understanding when different models are useful and how to employ them. The course helps students 1) identify appropriate statistical models that describe different data types and 2) design studies that enable causal inference (as opposed to merely establishing correlation).

Many of the phenomena political scientists take interest in can be classified into categories or events. This includes variables like voters&#39; choice of party, number of violent incidences in a time span, or time between violent events. The course introduces students to a number of models which are specifically designed to describe the underlying phenomenon that generates such data. The focus of the first part of the course is on correlations. Our purpose is to help students gear the statistical analysis towards a realistic description of the data.

Beyond statistical description, researchers&#39; interest in political phenomena is often motivated by a wish to identify their causes. Causal claims focus on whether we would continue to observe $y$ even in the absence of $x$. This is a typical question when studying the effect of policies, for example. The potential outcomes framework helps us understand the conditions under which we can identify causal relationships.  The second part of the course is devoted to a set of quantitative research designs that can be used to make causal inferences.


**Learning outcome**  Students will get hands-on practice by learning how to implement the various techniques and by replicating existing studies in R. Students will also learn how to present results in a manner that is understandable to a general audience, for example by using graphs and other visual tools. 

**More information** about the course is available at the [University of Oslo&#39;s webpages](https://www.uio.no/studier/emner/sv/statsvitenskap/STV4020B/).

&lt;div&gt;
&lt;object data=&#34;syllabus&#34; type=&#34;application/pdf&#34; width=&#34;700&#34; height=&#34;950&#34;&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;syllabus_stv4020b.pdf&#34;&gt;Download the syllabus&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/object&gt;
&lt;/div&gt; 

### Readings
We will use the following assigned readings:

* *Ward and Ahlquist (2018)* will introduce students to maximum likelihood as a framework for statistical modelling, different generalized linear models suited for various data types frequently encountered in political science, model selection strategies, and methods for interpreting and presenting empirical results.  This is the resource we will use for the first part of the course. 
* Chapters 1-3 in *Morgan and Winship (2015)* will  introduce  students  to  the  potential outcomes framework for causal inference and causal graphs, while *Samii (2016)* reviews the turn towards “causal empiricism” in political science that builds on these ideas.
* *Ho et al. (2007)* and *Iacus, King and Porro (2011)* introduce matching as a technique to adjust for observed confounders. 
* Chapter 4 in *Angrist and Pischke (2014)* will introduce students to regression discontinuity designs, while *Imbens and Lemieux (2008)* provide more detailed advice for the use of this design in applied research. 
* Chapter 5 in *Angrist and Pischke (2014)* will introduce students to difference-in-differences designs, while *Wing, Simon and Bello-Gomez (2018)* provide more detailed advice for the use of this design in applied research. 
* *Sovey and Green (2011)* introduce instrumental variables and provide guidelines for their application in political science. 

Some students may find some of the readings (such as Ward and Ahlquist (2018)) to be technically demanding. If so:  Do not despair!  We will use the lectures to clarify and provide intuition.  However, we do encourage you to not skip the equations.  A useful approach is to engage actively with the examples.  Working through as much as possible of the maths will give you a much better grasp of the material.

**Recommended readings**

Sometimes we understand things better when they are explained in different ways.  You may find it useful to consult the following books for alternative explanations throughout the course:  Fox (2008) and Stock and Watson (2012) are useful for thefirst part of the course (weeks 1-3), Cunningham (forthcoming) is useful for the second part of the course (weeks 4-5), and Hermansen (2019) is useful for getting up to speed in R.

---&gt;
&lt;!---## Flexibility
This feature can be used for publishing content such as:

* **Online courses**
* **Project or software documentation**
* **Tutorials**

The `courses` folder may be renamed. For example, we can rename it to `docs` for software/project documentation or `tutorials` for creating an online course.

## Delete tutorials

**To remove these pages, delete the `courses` folder and see below to delete the associated menu link.**

## Update site menu

After renaming or deleting the `courses` folder, you may wish to update any `[[main]]` menu links to it by editing your menu configuration at `config/_default/menus.toml`.

For example, if you delete this folder, you can remove the following from your menu configuration:

```toml
[[main]]
  name = &#34;Courses&#34;
  url = &#34;courses/&#34;
  weight = 50
```

Or, if you are creating a software documentation site, you can rename the `courses` folder to `docs` and update the associated *Courses* menu configuration to:

```toml
[[main]]
  name = &#34;Docs&#34;
  url = &#34;docs/&#34;
  weight = 50
```

## Update the docs menu

If you use the *docs* layout, note that the name of the menu in the front matter should be in the form `[menu.X]` where `X` is the folder name. Hence, if you rename the `courses/example/` folder, you should also rename the menu definitions in the front matter of files within `courses/example/` from `[menu.example]` to `[menu.&lt;NewFolderName&gt;]`.
---&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Installere R-pakken</title>
      <link>https://siljehermansen.github.io/data/laerdegr/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Aug 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://siljehermansen.github.io/data/laerdegr/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.fagbokforlaget.no/L%C3%A6r-deg-R/I9788245022131&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Lær deg R&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt; er en innføringsbok i statistikkprogrammet R utgitt av Fagbokforlaget (2019). Boka er levert med datasett, øvelsesoppgaver og løsningsforslag, slik at du kan prøve deg på egen hånd. Her kan du laste ned denne nettressursen. Den kommer som en egen R-pakke.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pakken kan installeres fra lokal fil eller rett fra GitHub.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.fagbokforlaget.no/L%C3%A6r-deg-R/I9788245022131&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;laerdegr.jpg&#34; width=&#34;35%&#34; align=&#34;right&#34; alt=&#34;Lær deg R: En innføring i statistikkprogrammets muligheter. Forfatter: Silje Synnøve Lyder Hermansen&#34;&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;installere-fra-lokal-fil&#34;&gt;Installere fra lokal fil&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Denne løsningen gjøres i to skritt.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;På denne siden&lt;/strong&gt; laster du ned pakken ved å trykke på én av disse lenkene:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For alle operativsystemer:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/SiljeHermansen/laerdegR/raw/master/laerdegR_0.1.0.tar.gz&#34; download&gt;
&lt;button class=&#34;button&#34;&gt;&lt;i class=&#34;fa fa-download&#34;&gt;&lt;/i&gt; laerdegR_0.1.0.tar.gz&lt;/button&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Windows-brukere kan også benytte seg av denne:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/SiljeHermansen/laerdegR/raw/master/laerdegR_0.1.0.zip&#34; download&gt;
&lt;button class=&#34;button&#34;&gt;&lt;i class=&#34;fa fa-download&#34;&gt;&lt;/i&gt; laerdegR_0.1.0.zip&lt;/button&gt;
&lt;/a&gt; 
&lt;p&gt;Filen vil da lastes ned på din maskin. Om du ikke har spesifisert annet, vil den ligge i mappen som kalles &amp;ldquo;Downloads&amp;rdquo; på maskinen din.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;I RStudio&lt;/strong&gt; installerer du filen i R-biblioteket.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Klikk på fanen som kalles &amp;ldquo;Packages&amp;rdquo; i vinduet nederst til høyre.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Klikk så på &amp;ldquo;Install&amp;rdquo;. I kommunikasjonsvinduet som så åpner seg, skal du velge &amp;ldquo;Install from: Package Archive File&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Under &amp;ldquo;Package archive:&amp;rdquo; må du deretter klikke på &amp;ldquo;Browse&amp;rdquo; og navigere deg fram til filen du nettopp lastet ned.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Klikk så på &amp;ldquo;Install&amp;rdquo;. Nå skrives installasjonskommandoen til R, og R skal i rask rekkefølge gi deg beskjed i rød skrift om at pakken installeres, og i svart skrift at &lt;code&gt;package ‘laerdegR’ successfully unpacked and MD5 sums checked&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Om du møter på feilmeldinger, bør du sjekke at tilleggsargumentene i installasjonskoden er korrekte. Filadressa (&lt;code&gt;C:/Downloads/&lt;/code&gt;) vil åpenbart variere fra maskin til maskin.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Om du har valgt tar.gz-fil, må koden se slik ut.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;install.packages(&amp;quot;C:/Downloads/laerdegR_0.1.0.tar.gz&amp;quot;, repos = NULL, type = &amp;quot;source&amp;quot;)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;p&gt;Om du har valgt zip-fil, må koden se slik ut.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;install.packages(&amp;quot;C:/Downloads/laerdegR_0.1.0.zip&amp;quot;, repos = NULL, type = &amp;quot;binary&amp;quot;)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;installere-direkte-fra-github&#34;&gt;Installere direkte fra GitHub&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Denne løsningen krever mer manøvrering.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;I nettleseren:&lt;/strong&gt; Begynn med å laste ned og installere &lt;a href=&#34;https://cran.r-project.org/bin/windows/Rtools/&#34;&gt;RTools&lt;/a&gt; uten å åpne RStudio.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;I RStudio:&lt;/strong&gt; installere &lt;code&gt;devtools&lt;/code&gt;-pakken og hent den inn fra biblioteket.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;install.packages(&#39;devtools&#39;)
library(devtools)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;p&gt;Nå kan du laste ned og installere nettressursen direkte fra GitHubs sider.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;install_github(&amp;quot;SiljeHermansen/laerdegR&amp;quot;)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Lær deg R</title>
      <link>https://siljehermansen.github.io/publication/laerdegr/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Aug 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://siljehermansen.github.io/publication/laerdegr/</guid>
      <description>&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.fagbokforlaget.no/L%C3%A6r-deg-R/I9788245022131&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;laerdegr.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Lær deg R: En innføring i statistikkprogrammets muligheter. Forfatter: Silje Synnøve Lyder Hermansen&#34;&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Abstract&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; Velkommen til R-universet! &lt;em&gt;Lær deg R&lt;/em&gt; er introduksjonen for deg som ønsker et godt arbeidsverktøy for statistisk analyse.  R har vokst enormt i popularitet de siste årene, og med god grunn. R er gratis og dekker analysebehovene til nybegynnere så vel som eksperter.&lt;/p&gt;  
&lt;p&gt;Boka er skrevet for samfunnsviteren som tar sine første skritt innen kvantitativ metode. Statistikk er et håndverk mer enn en vitenskap. Derfor er verktøyet viktig. Vi jobber sammen i RStudio, og går gjennom analysestadiene skritt for skritt. Vi laster inn data, tilrettelegger dem, gjør foranalyser og regresjonsanalyser. Fokuset er på å forstå hva som skjer, og kommunisere resultatene.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Boka er levert med datasett, øvelsesoppgaver og løsningsforslag, slik at du kan prøve deg på egen hånd. Alt du trenger er en datamaskin, internett og denne boka.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Omtale&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Øyvind Stiansen har anmeldt boka i &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.idunn.no/tfs/2020/02/silje_synnoeve_lyder_hermansen_laer_deg_r_en_innfoering_i_st&#34;&gt;Tidsskrift for samfunnsforskning&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Lær deg R-pakken&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lær deg R-pakken er en nettressurs som gir deg tilgang til datasett og oppgaveløsninger som hører til boka. Du kan laste ned pakken som .tar.gz-fil eller som .zip-fil:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/SiljeHermansen/laerdegR/raw/master/laerdegR_0.1.0.tar.gz&#34; download&gt;
&lt;button class=&#34;button&#34;&gt;&lt;i class=&#34;fa fa-download&#34;&gt;&lt;/i&gt; laerdegR_0.1.0.tar.gz&lt;/button&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/SiljeHermansen/laerdegR/raw/master/laerdegR_0.1.0.zip&#34; download&gt;
&lt;button class=&#34;button&#34;&gt;&lt;i class=&#34;fa fa-download&#34;&gt;&lt;/i&gt; laerdegR_0.1.0.zip&lt;/button&gt;
&lt;/a&gt; 
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Det kan være lurt å lese instruksene om hvordan du kan &lt;a href=&#34;https://siljehermansen.github.io/data/laerdegr&#34;&gt;laste ned og installere laerdegR&lt;/a&gt;- pakken.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Innholdsfortegnelse&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Boka tar deg skritt for skritt gjennom en typisk forskningsprosess.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Vi begynner med å laste inn og tilrettelegge data, før vi går videre med beskrivende analyser. I siste del av boka kjører vi så regresjonsanalyser: OLS og logistisk regresjon. Vi har fokus på å forstå og tolke resultatene. Dette inkluderer også å vurdere modellens troverdighet gjennom ulike former for modellstatistikk.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div&gt;
&lt;object data=&#34;Innholdsfortegnelse.pdf&#34; type=&#34;application/pdf&#34; width=&#34;700&#34; height=&#34;950&#34;&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;Innholdsfortegnelse.pdf&#34;&gt;Innholdsfortegnelsen til Lær deg R (2019)&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/object&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;!---&lt;embed src=&#34;Innholdsfortegnelse.pdf&#34; width=&#34;700&#34; height=&#34;950&#34; alt=&#34;Innholdsfortegnelse til Lær deg R&#34; pluginspage=&#34;http://www.adobe.com/products/acrobat/readstep2.html&#34;&gt;
---&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Reference&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Hermansen, Silje Synnøve Lyder (2019) &lt;a href=&#34;Innhold_bibliografi.pdf&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Lær deg R: En innføring i statistikkprogrammets muligheter&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, Bergen: Fagbokforlaget.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Samfunnsvitenskapelig forskningsmetode (SFS10207)</title>
      <link>https://siljehermansen.github.io/teaching/sfs10207/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Aug 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://siljehermansen.github.io/teaching/sfs10207/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Bachelornivå. &lt;em&gt;Høgskolen i Østfold. Avdeling for økonomi, språk og samfunnsfag.&lt;/em&gt; 2013&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Formålet med dette faget er å gi deg en introduksjon til hvordan vi oppnår kunnskap om samfunnet vi lever i. Samfunnsvitenskapelig forskningsmetode er et obligatorisk emne for studenter som ønsker en bachelor i statsvitenskap ved Høgskolen i Østfold.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lysark fra forelseningene finnes her:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Uke 34: &lt;a href=&#34;./Uke34/Presentation1.pdf&#34;&gt;Hva er vitenskap?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Uke 41: &lt;a href=&#34;./Uke41/Eksperimenter.pdf&#34;&gt;Eksperimenter&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Uke 42: &lt;a href=&#34;./Uke42/Forelesning3.pdf&#34;&gt;Valg av studieobjekt&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Uke 43: &lt;a href=&#34;./Uke43/Forelesning4.pdf&#34;&gt;Univariate fordelinger&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Uke 44: &lt;a href=&#34;./Uke44/Forelesning5.pdf&#34;&gt;Multivariate fordelinger&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Uke 45: &lt;a href=&#34;./Uke45/Forelesning6.pdf&#34;&gt;Gyldighet og reliabilitet&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Uke 46: &lt;a href=&#34;./Uke46/Forelesning7.pdf&#34;&gt;Kjikvadrattesten&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Emnebeskrivelse finner du &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.hiof.no/studier/emner/oss/2013/host/sfs10207.html&#34;&gt;her&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
