<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Candidate selection on Silje Synnøve Lyder Hermansen</title>
    <link>https://siljehermansen.github.io/tags/candidate-selection/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Candidate selection on Silje Synnøve Lyder Hermansen</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 24 Nov 2021 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	    <atom:link href="https://siljehermansen.github.io/tags/candidate-selection/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Introducing COMEPELDA: Comprehensive European Parliament electoral data covering rules, parties and candidates</title>
      <link>https://siljehermansen.github.io/publication/eup2021/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Nov 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://siljehermansen.github.io/publication/eup2021/</guid>
      <description>&lt;!---
&lt;a href=&#34;&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;EffectOfSpecialization.png&#34; alt=&#34;The positive effect of staying in the same committee decreases over time.&#34;&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;
---&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Abstract&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We introduce a new collection of data that consolidates information on European Parliament elections into one comprehensive source. It provides information on formal electoral rules as well as national-level and district-level election results for parties and individual politicians (including full candidate lists). The use of existing and new key variables makes it easy to link the data across the different units of observation (country, party, candidate, member of parliament) and join them with external information. Currently, the data cover four elections (1999–2014). Among other aspects, the collection should facilitate research on the European Parliament&#39;s allegedly weak electoral connection. In this article, we outline the main features of the datasets, describe patterns of intra-party competition and preference voting and conduct exploratory analyses of individual-level changes in list positions.&lt;/p&gt; 
&lt;!---
**Replication files** can be downloaded [here](https://github.com/SiljeHermansen/Replication-files)
---&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Reference&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Däubler, Thomas, Mihail Chiru, Silje Synnøve Lyder Hermansend (2021) &amp;ldquo;Introducing COMEPELDA: Comprehensive European Parliament electoral data covering rules, parties and candidates&amp;rdquo; &lt;em&gt;European Union Politics&lt;/em&gt;, 0(0), 1-21.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Striving for influence: The effect of performance on candidate selection</title>
      <link>https://siljehermansen.github.io/publication/pp2018/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Jul 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://siljehermansen.github.io/publication/pp2018/</guid>
      <description>&lt;a href=&#34;https://journals.sagepub.com/doi/full/10.1177/1354068816663036&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;reselection_performance.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Effect of signals of performance on incumbent candidate selection to the European Parliament. Author: Silje Hermansen.&#34;&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Abstract&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I consider how asymmetric information between the party selectorate and members of Parliament affects the renomination of incumbent candidates. By applying an adverse selection model, I argue that the selectorate looks to past performance to select candidates it expects will gain influence. However, the impact of performance varies according to the need for and availability of information.&lt;/p&gt; 
  &lt;p&gt;The European Parliament (EP) provides a most-likely case for information asymmetry. Studying three elections in 11 member states, I find that the allocation of influential positions in office improves chances of reselection. The effect increases when the allocation is more selective, and when the prior uncertainty around candidacies is high. The study thus proposes a new approach to the relationship between national parties and transnational groups in the EP. It also suggests venues for research on parliamentary politics and candidate selection in general. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Replication files&lt;/strong&gt; can be downloaded &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/SiljeHermansen/Replication-files&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Reference&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Hermansen, Silje Synnøve Lyder (2018) &amp;ldquo;Striving for influence: The effect of performance on candidate selection&amp;rdquo; &lt;em&gt;Party Politics&lt;/em&gt; 24 (4), 382-396.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Choosing Agents: Members of the European Parliament and their Political Organizations Seen through Report Allocation</title>
      <link>https://siljehermansen.github.io/publication/phd2017/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 10 Mar 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://siljehermansen.github.io/publication/phd2017/</guid>
      <description>&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.duo.uio.no/bitstream/handle/10852/69004/PhD-LyderHermansen-2017.pdf?sequence=4&amp;isAllowed=y&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;committee_activity.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Graphic illustrating the variation in committee activity in the European Parliament (1999-2014). Author: Silje Synnøve Lyder Hermansen&#34;&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Abstract&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This dissertation treats with partisan organization in the European Parliament (EP) and its impact on members’ (MEPs) career opportunities. National parties organize elections. Parliamentary work is organized around transnational political groups. They do not share any overarching organizational structure. My contributions pertain to the interconnected choices made by MEPs and their two party organizations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Parliamentary groups face a trade-off between the need for expertise and the risk of agency drift. Groups allocate reports to maximize the value added by the rapporteur while limiting the drift. They prefer policy experts to generalists and -- up to a point -- experienced MEPs to newcomers. Groups also balance individual demands with the collective need.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;National parties do not have institutionalized presence in the EP. They enter into an outcome-based contract similar to voters. MEPs are either rewarded by reselection or kicked out of office. Report alloca-tions dissipate uncertainty about MEPs’ ability. They thus improve MEPs’ career prospects to the extent that parties need new information about agent quality, and to the extent that parliamentary groups can provide it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Outreach&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A popularized presentation in Norwegian on the effect of gender quotas on legislative behavior and parties&#39; candidate selection can be found here: &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.sv.uio.no/isv/forskning/aktuelt/aktuelle-saker/2017/et-forsvar-for-kvinnekvotering-.html&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Et forsvar for kvinnekvotering&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Reference&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Hermansen, Silje Synnøve Lyder (2017) &lt;em&gt;Choosing Agents: Members of the European Parliament and their Political Organizations Seen through Report Allocation&lt;/em&gt;. Doctoral dissertation. University of Oslo. 323 p.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
