<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Projects on Silje Synnøve Lyder Hermansen</title>
    <link>https://siljehermansen.github.io/project/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Projects on Silje Synnøve Lyder Hermansen</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 20 Jan 2024 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	    <atom:link href="https://siljehermansen.github.io/project/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>External strategic interactions - the CJEU in relation with other actors</title>
      <link>https://siljehermansen.github.io/project/court-strategies/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 20 Jan 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://siljehermansen.github.io/project/court-strategies/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;How does the CJEU relate to its external interlocutors; litigants, the legal community and governments? These projects argue that the CJEU actively seeks alliance partners beyond governments. They also explore how the Court pursues its own interests without running against member states&amp;rsquo; wishes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;courting-litigants-relationship-with-civil-society&#34;&gt;Courting litigants: relationship with civil society&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&amp;ldquo;Leveling and Spotlighting: How International Courts Refract Private Litigation to Build Institutional Legitimacy&amp;rdquo;&lt;/strong&gt; with &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.tommasopavone.com/&#34;&gt;Tommaso Pavone&lt;/a&gt; and Louisa Boulaziz  presented at EUSA 2022 (Miami)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Private actors are increasingly turning to international courts (ICs). We argue that ICs can refract private litigation to build legitimacy and mitigate intergovernmental backlash. By leveling the odds for individuals and spotlighting their claims over those of more resourceful litigants, ICs cultivate civil society support and legitimate judicial policymaking in intergovernmental polities where individuals are disempowered. We evaluate this argument by scrutinizing the first IC with private access: the European Court of Justice (ECJ). We trace how ECJ judges privilege individuals in their advocacy and assess if they match words with deeds. Leveraging an original dataset, we find that the ECJ &amp;ldquo;levels&amp;rdquo;, supporting individual claims over businesses boasting larger and more experienced legal teams. The ECJ also &amp;ldquo;spotlights&amp;rdquo; its support for individuals through press releases that get amplified in law reviews. Our findings challenge the view that ICs build legitimacy by stealth and the ``haves&amp;rsquo;&amp;rsquo; come out ahead in litigation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!---
&lt;html&gt;
&lt;head&gt;&lt;title&gt;Shiny App Iframe&lt;/title&gt;&lt;/head&gt;
&lt;body&gt;
&lt;iframe id=&#34;lawyers shiny app&#34; src=&#34;https://siljehermansen.shinyapps.io/Lawyers/&#34; style=&#34;border: none; width: 100%; height: 950px&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/body&gt;
&lt;/html&gt;
--&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A draft of the paper can be found &lt;a href=&#34;https://preprints.apsanet.org/engage/api-gateway/apsa/assets/orp/resource/item/6614579d91aefa6ce12324d9/original/leveling-and-spotlighting-how-the-european-court-of-justice-favors-the-weak-to-promote-its-legitimacy.pdf&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-courts-relationship-with-governments&#34;&gt;The Court&amp;rsquo;s relationship with governments&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Judicious judging: The effects of political division on decision making in the European Court of Justice&lt;/strong&gt; with &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.eui.eu/people?id=urska-sadl&#34;&gt;Urska Sadl&lt;/a&gt; presented at APSA 2022 (Montréal)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How do courts react to political debate? Their legitimacy hinges on their ability to uphold the law impervious to political pressure. The authority of the ruling follows from the court&amp;rsquo;s reputation as apolitical. Politicization – understood as salient questions that divide stakeholders – threatens to erode this image. It imposes conflicting demands: Courts can prove their worth by solving questions for which there is a demand for a legal solution, but they risk their reputation in a politically divided environment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;Integration_sd_over_time.png&#34; width=&#34;50%&#34; align=&#34;right&#34; alt=&#34;The number of judgements with wide legal ambit is low when member state governments have diverse preferences on European integration, and more numerous when government preferences are more homogeneous.&#34;/&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Literature on judicial independence focuses on direct and explicit threats issued by the political branch. Arguments of legislative override typically predict that political division empowers the judiciary. In contrast, we argue that courts are sensitive even to the potential eruption of conflict because they value their diffuse legitimacy. Effective judicial policy making is thus a question of strategic timing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To test our theory, we study the European Court of Justice. Known as the “dark horse of integration”, it is an independent court with political sway. Yet political considerations profoundly affects its decision making. We draw on unprecedented data mapping out the legal ambit of all preliminary cases relating to the Free movement of people throughout the history. We find that the Court holds back on the legal ambit of rulings, preferring to bolster its institutional authority, in times of political division. Reversely, it broadens the ambit when salience is high and conflict low. Thus, when salience and division combine, they null each other out; leaving traces only in the decision-making process.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!--
# &lt;html&gt;
# &lt;head&gt;&lt;title&gt;plotly&lt;/title&gt;&lt;/head&gt;
# &lt;body&gt;
# &lt;iframe id=&#34;legal ambit webpage&#34; src=&#34;legal_ambit_trivariate.html&#34; style=&#34;border: none; width: 100%; height: 600px&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
# &lt;/body&gt;
# &lt;/html&gt;
 
# &lt;div include-html=&#34;legal_ambit_trivariate.html&#34;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
--&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Litigating in the European Court of Justice: Lawyers&amp;rsquo; influence on supranational decision-making&lt;/strong&gt; with &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.tommasopavone.com/&#34;&gt;Tommaso Pavone&lt;/a&gt; and Louisa Boulaziz presented at ECPR 2021 (zoom)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This paper assesses how private litigants’ propensity to win cases before international courts is conditioned by the quality of their legal counsel and by the constraints of intergovernmental politics. Building on legal mobilization and party capability theories, we argue that quality legal counsel bolsters a private party’s capacity to convey legal information to judges that is relevant to deciding the case in their favor. At the same time, we build on intergovernmentalist theories of international adjudication positing that judges will also be sensitive to political signals by national governments. As a result, we hypothesize that the influence of quality legal counsel on international judges is conditioned by the political support that member states&amp;rsquo; express.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To assess these claims, we exploit an original dataset of parties and lawyers involved in disputes before the European Court of Justice (ECJ) – arguably the most successful and influential international court procuring access to private litigants. We find being represented by a lawyer bolsters the probability that litigants submit observations and win cases before the ECJ, yet this effect is the highest in the minority of cases where a majority of more member state governments intervene in favor of the applicant. We conclude by highlighting the necessity of combining theories of legal mobilization and intergovernmental politics in order to explain judicial decision-making in international courts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!--* **&#34;Measuring the evolution of CJEU case law using word embeddings&#34;** presented at Big Insight - a center for research-based innovation, Norwegian Computing Center 2019 (Oslo)

To study the conditions for judicial activism – self-restraint, initiation or expansion of case law – we need a consistent and comparable measure of court output. Can machine learning help us in this respect? This research note discusses ways of comparing court documents in order to obtain such measures. The focus is on word embeddings, which allow researchers to identify similar – but not identical – terms and use them as building blocks for document-level comparisons.

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;Effect_of_judgment_similarity_on_academic_attention.png&#34; width=&#34;50%&#34; align=&#34;left&#34; alt=&#34;Effect of judgment similarity on academic attention (annotations in legal journals).&#34;/&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

Analyzing the evolution of case law requires researchers to read and compare judgments. It is a resource-intensive process both in terms of competence and number of working hours. Assessing the outcome of a case typically requires familiarity with legal precedent in the court, the doctrines under- pinning rulings as well at the type of cases brought before the tribunal. In other words, - depending on the task – the researcher needs a good grasp of similar cases in the past (i.e. legal precedent) and/or the future (i.e. its value as a precedent) as well as the field-specific vocabulary.

The purpose of this research note is to train a model to make such comparisons for us. To obtain word embeddings, I apply a word2vec algorithm on 30999 (machine-readable) legal texts produced by the members of the Court of Justice of the European Union (CJEU) itself. I use these to construct a do- main specific vocabulary of similar words. The similarities can then be used to identify and compare relevant documents based on their word occurrences.

A draft version can be found [here](WordEmbeddings_Hermansen.pdf).
--&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Judicial behavior: Decision makers in the CJEU</title>
      <link>https://siljehermansen.github.io/project/judicial-behavior/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 20 Jan 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://siljehermansen.github.io/project/judicial-behavior/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Little research exists on how judges enter the Court and how its internal organization affects decision making.  This project opens the black box of these decision-making processes to consider governments’ and judges’ strategic behavior.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I show that judges&amp;rsquo; performance and governments&amp;rsquo; political preferences are intertwined both when judges are appointed and when influence is distributed within the Court.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;judicial-appointments-to-the-cjeu&#34;&gt;Judicial appointments to the CJEU&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&amp;ldquo;Shaping the Bench: The Effect of Ideology, Impact, and Information Quality on Judicial Reappointments&amp;rdquo;&lt;/strong&gt;  with Daniel Naurin presented at the ECPR Joint Sessions 2019 (Mons)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;Effectplot_preferences_economy_CJ.jpeg&#34; width=&#34;50%&#34; align=&#34;right&#34; alt=&#34;Graphic showing that the likelihood of replacing a sitting judge increases with the distance between the economic preferences of the appointing and reappointing government.&#34;/&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Courts’ institutional design has significant implications for judicial independence and accountability, particularly when terms are renewable. Policy-seeking selectors often consider judges’ past service to predict their future policy impact. However, the same judicial record may carry more or less weight in the assessment, depending on the court’s case-management process.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Drawing on original data on reappointments to the Court of Justice of the European Union, we show that reappointments are made based on both ideology and impact. Transparent, selective allocation of influential positions in the court favors the retention of high-impact judges, while non-selective allocations do not. Secret voting &amp;ndash; conventionally seen as safeguarding judicial independence &amp;ndash; also does not shield judges against ideological deselection. Our analysis unveils new insights into when judicial accountability incentivizes effort. It also challenges the prevailing belief that renewable terms decrease judicial independence, instead suggesting that selectors partially rely on evaluations by court members for reappointment decisions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A draft version can be found &lt;a href=&#34;Shaping_the_bench_HermansenNaurin.pdf&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&amp;ldquo;How do merit commissions affect judicial behavior? Evidence from the Court of Justice of the European Union&amp;rdquo;&lt;/strong&gt;  with Sivaram Cheruvu, Joshua Fjelstul, and Daniel Naurin presented at APSA 2022 (Montréal)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;Coefplot_panel255.jpg&#34; width=&#34;50%&#34; align=&#34;right&#34; alt=&#34;.&#34;/&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Governments create monitoring entities to ensure that policymakers are working effectively. Monitors&amp;rsquo; control over retaining and selecting policymakers, however, may create incentives that lead to sub-optimal outcomes. One such entity is a merit commission (also known as a judicial council) that evaluates judges subject to retention and (or) selection. How do merit commissions affect judicial behavior? We construct a formal model arguing that lower competence incumbent judges only subject to merit retention will complete cases more quickly at the expense of quality opinion-writing, as their productivity is a signal of their effort investment to the commission. Conversely, judges subject to merit selection and subsequent retention will not make the same tradeoff, as the commission&amp;rsquo;s initial selection of them makes it more costly for the commission to negatively evaluate them upon retention. We provide evidence leveraging the Article 255 panel for (re)appointments to the Court of Justice of the European Union.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;published-work&#34;&gt;Published work&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If who makes decisions within courts matters for the outcome of cases and their reception, then studying how cases and judges are matched is essential to understanding judicial independence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://siljehermansen.github.io/publication/jlc2023/&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;The CJEU Database Platform: Decisions and Decision-Makers&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;  (2023)  with Stein Arne Brekke, Joshua Fjelstul and Daniel Naurin. &lt;em&gt;Journal of Law and Courts&lt;/em&gt; 0(0), 1-22.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://siljehermansen.github.io/publication/jepp2020/&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Building legitimacy: strategic case allocations in the Court of Justice of the European Union&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;  (2020) &lt;em&gt;Journal of European Public Policy&lt;/em&gt; 27 (8), 1215-1235.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Decision makers in the European Parliament (EP)</title>
      <link>https://siljehermansen.github.io/project/european-parliament/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 24 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://siljehermansen.github.io/project/european-parliament/</guid>
      <description>&lt;!---
&lt;img src=&#34;EP.jpg&#34; align=&#34;centre&#34;, caption = &#34;The European Parliament in Strasbourg&#34;/&gt;
---&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Political parties obtain influence through their choice of representatives. &lt;em&gt;Outside&lt;/em&gt; of parliament, they gain sway through the candidates for whom they secure election. &lt;em&gt;Inside&lt;/em&gt; parliament, party groups shape policies through the allocation of tasks to competent members. This project delves into the mutual influence of parliamentary group allocations and the choices made by extra-parliamentary party organizations. In the center are members of Parliament whose political careers are shaped by both actors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;election-seeking&#34;&gt;Election seeking&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;National parties do not have institutionalized presence in the EP. Their position is instead close to that of voters: They can hold representatives accountable by observing how they perform in office and either reselect or replace incumbent candidates in the next election. One important source of information for parties is the responsibilities that MEPs obtain from their transnational party leadership. This project looks at how parties&amp;rsquo; uncertainty and access to new information determine the electoral accountability of Members of the European Parliament (MEPs).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;ongoing-work&#34;&gt;Ongoing work&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;!--
* **&#34;Blurred lines between electoral and parliamentary representation:  The use of constituency staff among European Members of Parliament&#34;** with [Andreja Pegan](http://www.pegan.org/). Working paper.

Political actors receive public funding to execute their mandate. Spending that money for electoral purposes, however, undermines democratic representation.

We investigate to what extent parliamentary spending increases during campaign periods and how the electoral system affects such behavior. Specifically, we model within-individual changes in constituency-staff size among 1174 Members of the European Parliament. We find that local spending increases prior to both European and national elections and more so in candidate-centered systems.

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;Coefplot_ElectoralSystem.jpeg&#34; width=&#34;50%&#34; align=&#34;left&#34; alt=&#34;Coefplot displaying the predicted number of local assistants by electoral system.&#34;/&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;


We conclude that EU citizens are represented differently depending on their nationality. Insofar as constituency staff creates an incumbency advantage, the system also generates inequalities between candidates which public funding aims to equalize. Moreover, the attempt to mend Parliament’s democratic deficit by financing members’ contact with citizens also implies funding national electoral campaigns.

A draft version can be found [here](BlurredLines.pdf).
--&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&amp;ldquo;Lingering bias and representation quality: the effects of legislated gender quotas in the European Parliament&amp;rdquo;&lt;/strong&gt; Working paper.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How does biased political recruitment &amp;ndash; and the subsequent legislation of quotas &amp;ndash; affect the quality of representation ensured by women in Parliament?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I draw on insights from the literature on political agency to distinguish between the effects of selection and sanction. First, if recruitment in the absence of quotas implies higher requirements for women, then selected women are of higher quality. Second, when quotas lower the bar, new women enter office. However, parties are less certain about their quality and react by increasing accountability.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I investigate representation in the European Parliament  (1999-2014) before and after the legislation of quotas in several member states. Absent quotas, I find that biased selection leads to female representatives who aim at longer careers and perform better at equal levels of effort. When quotas are legislated, parties emphasize women&amp;rsquo;s record of service during reselection. Women are thus incentivized to provide more effort.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A draft version can be found &lt;a href=&#34;Gender.pdf&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A popularized presentation (in Norwegian) can be found &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.sv.uio.no/isv/forskning/aktuelt/aktuelle-saker/2017/et-forsvar-for-kvinnekvotering-.html&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;published-work&#34;&gt;Published work&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://siljehermansen.github.io/publication/eup2024/&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Blurred lines between electoral and parliamentary representation:  The use of constituency staff among Members of the European Parliament&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt; with &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.pegan.org/&#34;&gt;Andreja Pegan&lt;/a&gt; (2023) &lt;em&gt;European Union Politics&lt;/em&gt; 0 (0), 1-34.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://siljehermansen.github.io/publication/eup2022/&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Introducing COMEPELDA: Comprehensive European Parliament electoral data covering rules, parties and candidates&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt; with Thomas Däubler and Mihail Chiru   (2022) &lt;em&gt;European Union Politics&lt;/em&gt; 23 (2), 351-371.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://siljehermansen.github.io/publication/pp2018/&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Striving for influence: The effect of performance on candidate selection&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;  (2018) &lt;em&gt;Party Politics&lt;/em&gt; 24 (4), 382-396.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;legislative-behavior&#34;&gt;Legislative behavior&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The European Parliament (EP) is a committee-oriented legislature; meaning that the bulk of legislative work is done in committees.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Parliamentary groups face a trade-off between the need for expertise and the risk of agency drift. We argue that groups allocate reports to maximize the value added by the rapporteur while limiting the drift. They prefer loyal policy experts to generalists and &amp;ndash; up to a point &amp;ndash; experienced MEPs to newcomers. Groups also balance individual demands with the collective need.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;published-work-1&#34;&gt;Published work&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://siljehermansen.github.io/publication/eup2020/&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Delegation of committee reports in the European Parliament&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt; with Fang-Yi Chiou and Bjørn Høyland (2020) &lt;em&gt;European Union Politics&lt;/em&gt; 21 (2), 233-254.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://siljehermansen.github.io/publication/jls2018/&#34;&gt;&amp;quot;(Self-)selection and expertise among decision-makers in the European Parliament&amp;quot;&lt;/a&gt; (2018) &lt;em&gt;The Journal of Legislative Studies&lt;/em&gt; 24 (1), 148-172.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.duo.uio.no/bitstream/handle/10852/69004/PhD-LyderHermansen-2017.pdf?sequence=4&amp;amp;isAllowed=y&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Choosing Agents: Members of the European Parliament and their political organizations seen through report allocation&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt; (2017) Doctoral dissertation, &lt;em&gt;University of Oslo&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
