<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Political accountability on Silje Synnøve Lyder Hermansen</title>
    <link>https://siljehermansen.github.io/tags/political-accountability/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Political accountability on Silje Synnøve Lyder Hermansen</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 11 Dec 2021 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	    <atom:link href="https://siljehermansen.github.io/tags/political-accountability/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Decision makers in the European Parliament (EP)</title>
      <link>https://siljehermansen.github.io/project/european-parliament/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 11 Dec 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://siljehermansen.github.io/project/european-parliament/</guid>
      <description>&lt;!---
&lt;img src=&#34;EP.jpg&#34; align=&#34;centre&#34;, caption = &#34;The European Parliament in Strasbourg&#34;/&gt;
---&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Political parties obtain influence through their choice of representatives. &lt;em&gt;Outside&lt;/em&gt; of parliament, they gain sway through the candidates for whom they secure election. &lt;em&gt;Inside&lt;/em&gt; parliament party groups shape policies through the allocation of tasks to competent members. This project delves into the mutual influence of parliamentary group allocations and the choices made by extra-parliamentary party organizations. In the center are members of Parliament whose political careers are shaped by both actors. In the center are members of Parliament whose political careers are shaped by both actors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;election-seeking&#34;&gt;Election seeking&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;National parties do not have institutionalized presence in the EP. They enter
into an outcome-based contract similar to voters. MEPs are either rewarded by reselection or kicked out of office. Report allocations dissipate uncertainty about MEPs’ ability. They thus improve MEPs’ career prospects to the extent that parties need new information about agent quality, and to the extent that parliamentary groups can provide it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;ongoing-work&#34;&gt;Ongoing work&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&amp;ldquo;Blurred lines between electoral and parliamentary representation:  The use of constituency staff among European Members of Parliament&amp;rdquo;&lt;/strong&gt; with &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.pegan.org/&#34;&gt;Andreja Pegan&lt;/a&gt;, presented at EPSA Annual Meeting 2017 (Vienna)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Political actors receive public funding to execute their mandate. Spending that money for electoral purposes, however, undermines democratic representation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We investigate to what extent parliamentary spending increases during campaign periods and how the electoral system affects such behavior. Specifically, we model within-individual changes in constituency-staff size among 1174 Members of the European Parliament. We find that local spending increases prior to both European and national elections and more so in candidate-centered systems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;Coefplot_ElectoralSystem.jpeg&#34; width=&#34;50%&#34; align=&#34;left&#34; alt=&#34;Coefplot displaying the predicted number of local assistants by electoral system.&#34;/&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We conclude that EU citizens are represented differently depending on their nationality. Insofar as constituency staff creates an incumbency advantage, the system also generates inequalities between candidates which public funding aims to equalize. Moreover, the attempt to mend Parliament’s democratic deficit by financing members’ contact with citizens also implies funding national electoral campaigns.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A draft version can be found &lt;a href=&#34;BlurredLines.pdf&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&amp;ldquo;How Do Legislated Gender Quotas Impact Representation?&amp;quot;&lt;/strong&gt; Working paper presented at EPSA Annual Meeting 2016 (Brussels)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How does biased political recruitment – and the subsequent legislation of quotas – affect the quality of women’s performance as representatives in Parliament? I draw on insights from the literature on political agency to distinguish between the effects of selection and sanction.  First, if recruitment in the absence of quotas implies higher requirements for women, then selected women are of higher quality. Second, when quotas lower the bar, new women enter office.  However, parties are less certain about the quality of these women and react by increasing accountability.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I investigate representation in the European Parliament (1999-2014) before and after the legislation of quotas in several member states.  Absent quotas, I find that biased selection leads to female representatives who pursue longer careers and perform better at equal levels of effort. When quotas are legislated, parties emphasize women’s service records during reselection.  Women are thus incentivized to put in more effort.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A draft version can be found &lt;a href=&#34;Gender.pdf&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A popularized presentation (in Norwegian) can be found &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.sv.uio.no/isv/forskning/aktuelt/aktuelle-saker/2017/et-forsvar-for-kvinnekvotering-.html&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;published-work&#34;&gt;Published work&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://siljehermansen.github.io/publication/eup2021/&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Introducing COMEPELDA: Comprehensive European Parliament electoral data covering rules, parties and candidates&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;  (2021) &lt;em&gt;European Union Politics&lt;/em&gt; with Thomas Däubler and Mihail Chiru 0 (0), 1-21.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://siljehermansen.github.io/publication/pp2018/&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Striving for influence: The effect of performance on candidate selection&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;  (2018) &lt;em&gt;Party Politics&lt;/em&gt; 24 (4), 382-396.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;legislative-behavior&#34;&gt;Legislative behavior&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The European Parliament (EP) is a committee-oriented legislature; meaning that the bulk of legislative work is done in committees.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Parliamentary groups face a trade-off between the need for expertise and the risk of agency drift. We argue that groups allocate reports to maximize the value added by the rapporteur while limiting the drift. They prefer loyal policy experts to generalists and &amp;ndash; up to a point &amp;ndash; experienced MEPs to newcomers. Groups also balance individual demands with the collective need.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;published-work-1&#34;&gt;Published work&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://siljehermansen.github.io/publication/eup2020/&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Delegation of committee reports in the European Parliament&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt; with Fang-Yi Chiou and Bjørn Høyland (2020) &lt;em&gt;European Union Politics&lt;/em&gt; 21 (2), 233-254.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://siljehermansen.github.io/publication/jls2018/&#34;&gt;&amp;quot;(Self-)selection and expertise among decision-makers in the European Parliament&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt; (2018) &lt;em&gt;The Journal of Legislative Studies&lt;/em&gt; 24 (1), 148-172.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.duo.uio.no/bitstream/handle/10852/69004/PhD-LyderHermansen-2017.pdf?sequence=4&amp;amp;isAllowed=y&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Choosing Agents: Members of the European Parliament and their political organizations seen through report allocation&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt; (2017) Doctoral dissertation, &lt;em&gt;University of Oslo&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Building legitimacy: strategic case allocations in the Court of Justice of the European Union</title>
      <link>https://siljehermansen.github.io/publication/jepp2020/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://siljehermansen.github.io/publication/jepp2020/</guid>
      <description>&lt;!---
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;MarginalEffect_First_B_item_Current_government_-_weighted0.jpeg&#34; width=&#34;50%&#34; align=&#34;left&#34; alt=&#34;No effect of government preferences in non-politicized cases.&#34;/&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;MarginalEffect_First_B_item_Current_government_-_weighted1.jpeg&#34; width=&#34;50%&#34; align=&#34;right&#34; alt=&#34;Effect of government preferences in politicized cases. Author: Silje Synnøve Lyder Hermansen.&#34;/&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;small&gt;Figure: Judges whose governments hold outlying economic preferences are less likely to act as rapporteur in court cases that could divide member states.&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
---&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;NotDebatedLegislation.jpeg&#34; width=&#34;50%&#34; align=&#34;left&#34; alt=&#34;No effect of government preferences in non-politicized cases.&#34;/&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;DebatedLegislation.jpeg&#34; width=&#34;50%&#34; align=&#34;right&#34; alt=&#34;Effect of government preferences in politicized cases. Author: Silje Synnøve Lyder Hermansen.&#34;/&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;small&gt;Figure: Judges whose governments hold outlying economic preferences are less likely to act as rapporteur in court cases that could divide member states.&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Abstract&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Does the President of the Court of Justice of the European Union (CJEU) make strategic use of his members?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cases in the CJEU areprepared  by  a  “judge-rapporteur”  who  acts  as  an  agenda  setter. I argue that the President builds the Court’s legitimacy by strategically allocating cases to select judges.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Using original data on 9623 case allocations (1980-2015), I argue that suspicions about judges’ political accountability can polarize already politicized debates.  The President circumvents such dynamicsby  appointing  a  rapporteur  whose  government  holds  moderate  political  preferences.   However,  he  considers  governmental  preferencesand disagreements mainly when case law is not yet developed.  This may  also  contribute  to  explaining  judges individual-level  specialization, which arguably favors the construction of a coherent case law.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The results speak to the lingering effect of judges’ renewable terms &amp;ndash; despite secret voting &amp;ndash; as well as the importance of courts internalorganization for judicial independence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Reference&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Hermansen, Silje Synnøve Lyder (2020) &lt;a href=&#34;http://dx.doi.org/10.1080/13501763.2020.1714697&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Building legitimacy: strategic case allocations in the Court of Justice of the European Union&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt; &lt;em&gt;Journal of European Public Policy&lt;/em&gt;, 27(8), pp 1215-1235&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Striving for influence: The effect of performance on candidate selection</title>
      <link>https://siljehermansen.github.io/publication/pp2018/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Jul 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://siljehermansen.github.io/publication/pp2018/</guid>
      <description>&lt;a href=&#34;https://journals.sagepub.com/doi/full/10.1177/1354068816663036&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;reselection_performance.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Effect of signals of performance on incumbent candidate selection to the European Parliament. Author: Silje Hermansen.&#34;&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Abstract&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I consider how asymmetric information between the party selectorate and members of Parliament affects the renomination of incumbent candidates. By applying an adverse selection model, I argue that the selectorate looks to past performance to select candidates it expects will gain influence. However, the impact of performance varies according to the need for and availability of information.&lt;/p&gt; 
  &lt;p&gt;The European Parliament (EP) provides a most-likely case for information asymmetry. Studying three elections in 11 member states, I find that the allocation of influential positions in office improves chances of reselection. The effect increases when the allocation is more selective, and when the prior uncertainty around candidacies is high. The study thus proposes a new approach to the relationship between national parties and transnational groups in the EP. It also suggests venues for research on parliamentary politics and candidate selection in general. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Replication files&lt;/strong&gt; can be downloaded &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/SiljeHermansen/Replication-files&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Reference&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Hermansen, Silje Synnøve Lyder (2018) &amp;ldquo;Striving for influence: The effect of performance on candidate selection&amp;rdquo; &lt;em&gt;Party Politics&lt;/em&gt; 24 (4), 382-396.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Choosing Agents: Members of the European Parliament and their Political Organizations Seen through Report Allocation</title>
      <link>https://siljehermansen.github.io/publication/phd2017/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 10 Mar 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://siljehermansen.github.io/publication/phd2017/</guid>
      <description>&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.duo.uio.no/bitstream/handle/10852/69004/PhD-LyderHermansen-2017.pdf?sequence=4&amp;isAllowed=y&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;committee_activity.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Graphic illustrating the variation in committee activity in the European Parliament (1999-2014). Author: Silje Synnøve Lyder Hermansen&#34;&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Abstract&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This dissertation treats with partisan organization in the European Parliament (EP) and its impact on members’ (MEPs) career opportunities. National parties organize elections. Parliamentary work is organized around transnational political groups. They do not share any overarching organizational structure. My contributions pertain to the interconnected choices made by MEPs and their two party organizations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Parliamentary groups face a trade-off between the need for expertise and the risk of agency drift. Groups allocate reports to maximize the value added by the rapporteur while limiting the drift. They prefer policy experts to generalists and -- up to a point -- experienced MEPs to newcomers. Groups also balance individual demands with the collective need.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;National parties do not have institutionalized presence in the EP. They enter into an outcome-based contract similar to voters. MEPs are either rewarded by reselection or kicked out of office. Report alloca-tions dissipate uncertainty about MEPs’ ability. They thus improve MEPs’ career prospects to the extent that parties need new information about agent quality, and to the extent that parliamentary groups can provide it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Outreach&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A popularized presentation in Norwegian on the effect of gender quotas on legislative behavior and parties&#39; candidate selection can be found here: &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.sv.uio.no/isv/forskning/aktuelt/aktuelle-saker/2017/et-forsvar-for-kvinnekvotering-.html&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Et forsvar for kvinnekvotering&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Reference&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Hermansen, Silje Synnøve Lyder (2017) &lt;em&gt;Choosing Agents: Members of the European Parliament and their Political Organizations Seen through Report Allocation&lt;/em&gt;. Doctoral dissertation. University of Oslo. 323 p.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
