<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Parliamentary behavior on Silje Synnøve Lyder Hermansen</title>
    <link>/tags/parliamentary-behavior/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Parliamentary behavior on Silje Synnøve Lyder Hermansen</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 01 Aug 2019 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	    <atom:link href="/tags/parliamentary-behavior/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Decision makers in the Court of Justice of the European Union (CJEU)</title>
      <link>/project/european-parliament/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Aug 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/project/european-parliament/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The Court of Justice of the European Union (CJEU) has established itself as the world’s most influential international court, functioning in many respects as a federal supreme court.  This project aims to better understand the conditions for -– and therefore the limits of -– the Court’s independence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I open the black box of the decision-making process to consider governments’ and judges’ strategic behavior. As of today, very little research exists on how judges enter the Court and how its internal organization affect decision-making.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I see two lacunas in the literature: First - although it has evolved - the focus on the CJEU as an international institution has prevented authors to draw on established theories of (domestic) court behavior. Paradoxically, this has also prevented the comparative research designs that make supranational institutions particularly interesting for the study of domestic institutions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Second, authors have focused on the Court’s output, treating the CJEU and member states as unitary actors. In contrast, this project opens the black box of the decision-making process to consider governments’ and judges’ strategic behavior.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The internal organization of the Court has become both more complex and more hierarchical over time.
&lt;img src=&#34;Timeline.gif&#34; alt=&#34;The internal organization of the Court has become both more complex and more hierarchical over time.&#34; /&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;./DecisionMakers_Hermansen.pdf&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
