<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Judicial behavior on Silje Synnøve Lyder Hermansen</title>
    <link>https://siljehermansen.github.io/tags/judicial-behavior/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Judicial behavior on Silje Synnøve Lyder Hermansen</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 12 Mar 2024 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	    <atom:link href="https://siljehermansen.github.io/tags/judicial-behavior/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>The European Court of Justice, an able and unwilling lawmaker: evidence from 920 free movement of persons judgments</title>
      <link>https://siljehermansen.github.io/publication/edvardelgar2024/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 12 Mar 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://siljehermansen.github.io/publication/edvardelgar2024/</guid>
      <description>&lt;!---
&lt;a href=&#34;&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;EffectOfSpecialization.png&#34; alt=&#34;The positive effect of staying in the same committee decreases over time.&#34;&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;
---&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Abstract&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Does the European Court of Justice respond to political divisions by authoritatively settling or cautiously avoiding salient legal matters? The existing literature suggests the former but this chapter, surveying 920 free movement of persons judgments, suggests the latter: the Court issues fewer audacious rulings in times of uneven political support while also disproportionately increasing chamber size. The findings cast the Court as a selectively audacious lawmaker, primarily concerned with procedural legitimacy. They nuance the established narrative of the Court as the motor of integration able and willing to make law in times of political stalemate and legislative paralysis. More broadly, the chapter demonstrates that courts do not make policy in lieu of legislators when and because they can but avoid policymaking if and until they can.&lt;/p&gt; 
&lt;!---
**Replication files** can be downloaded [here](https://github.com/SiljeHermansen/Replication-files)
---&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Reference&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Sadl, Urska, Silje Synnøve Lyder Hermansen (2024) &amp;ldquo;The European Court of Justice, an able and unwilling lawmaker: evidence from 920 free movement of persons judgments&amp;rdquo; &lt;em&gt;Revisiting Judicial Politics in the European Union&lt;/em&gt;, Ed. Mark Dawson, Elise Muir and Bruno deWitte. Edward Elgar Publishing. Chapter 14. pp. 282-304.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The CJEU Database Platform: Decisions and Decision-Makers</title>
      <link>https://siljehermansen.github.io/publication/jlc2023/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Jan 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://siljehermansen.github.io/publication/jlc2023/</guid>
      <description>&lt;!---
&lt;a href=&#34;&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;EffectOfSpecialization.png&#34; alt=&#34;The positive effect of staying in the same committee decreases over time.&#34;&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;
---&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Abstract&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This article presents the CJEU Database Platform, which provides scholars with an extensive
collection of easily accessible, research-ready data on the the universe of cases, decisions, and judges at the Court of Justice of the European Union (CJEU). The CJEU Database Platform
provides a foundation for the broader CJEU Database currently being developed by The
IUROPA Project, a multidisciplinary group of scholars researching judicial politics in the
European Union (EU). In this article, we illustrate how the CJEU Database Platform opens
the door to new areas of theoretical and empirical research on judicial politics in the EU.&lt;/p&gt; 
&lt;!---
**Replication files** can be downloaded [here](https://github.com/SiljeHermansen/Replication-files)
---&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Reference&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Brekke, Stein-Arne, Joshua Fjelstul, Silje Synnøve Lyder Hermansen, Daniel Naurin (2023) &amp;ldquo;The CJEU Database Platform: Decisions and Decision-Makers&amp;rdquo;. &lt;em&gt;The Journal of Law and Courts&lt;/em&gt;. 11(2), pp. 389-410.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Judicial behavior: Decision makers in the CJEU</title>
      <link>https://siljehermansen.github.io/project/judicial-behavior/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 20 Jan 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://siljehermansen.github.io/project/judicial-behavior/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Little research exists on how judges enter the Court and how its internal organization affects decision making.  This project opens the black box of these decision-making processes to consider governments’ and judges’ strategic behavior.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I show that judges&amp;rsquo; performance and governments&amp;rsquo; political preferences are intertwined both when judges are appointed and when influence is distributed within the Court.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;judicial-appointments-to-the-cjeu&#34;&gt;Judicial appointments to the CJEU&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&amp;ldquo;Shaping the Bench: The Effect of Ideology, Impact, and Information Quality on Judicial Reappointments&amp;rdquo;&lt;/strong&gt;  with Daniel Naurin presented at the ECPR Joint Sessions 2019 (Mons)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;Effectplot_preferences_economy_CJ.jpeg&#34; width=&#34;50%&#34; align=&#34;right&#34; alt=&#34;Graphic showing that the likelihood of replacing a sitting judge increases with the distance between the economic preferences of the appointing and reappointing government.&#34;/&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Courts’ institutional design has significant implications for judicial independence and accountability, particularly when terms are renewable. Policy-seeking selectors often consider judges’ past service to predict their future policy impact. However, the same judicial record may carry more or less weight in the assessment, depending on the court’s case-management process.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Drawing on original data on reappointments to the Court of Justice of the European Union, we show that reappointments are made based on both ideology and impact. Transparent, selective allocation of influential positions in the court favors the retention of high-impact judges, while non-selective allocations do not. Secret voting &amp;ndash; conventionally seen as safeguarding judicial independence &amp;ndash; also does not shield judges against ideological deselection. Our analysis unveils new insights into when judicial accountability incentivizes effort. It also challenges the prevailing belief that renewable terms decrease judicial independence, instead suggesting that selectors partially rely on evaluations by court members for reappointment decisions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A draft version can be found &lt;a href=&#34;Shaping_the_bench_HermansenNaurin.pdf&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&amp;ldquo;How do merit commissions affect judicial behavior? Evidence from the Court of Justice of the European Union&amp;rdquo;&lt;/strong&gt;  with Sivaram Cheruvu, Joshua Fjelstul, and Daniel Naurin presented at APSA 2022 (Montréal)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;Coefplot_panel255.jpg&#34; width=&#34;50%&#34; align=&#34;right&#34; alt=&#34;.&#34;/&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Governments create monitoring entities to ensure that policymakers are working effectively. Monitors&amp;rsquo; control over retaining and selecting policymakers, however, may create incentives that lead to sub-optimal outcomes. One such entity is a merit commission (also known as a judicial council) that evaluates judges subject to retention and (or) selection. How do merit commissions affect judicial behavior? We construct a formal model arguing that lower competence incumbent judges only subject to merit retention will complete cases more quickly at the expense of quality opinion-writing, as their productivity is a signal of their effort investment to the commission. Conversely, judges subject to merit selection and subsequent retention will not make the same tradeoff, as the commission&amp;rsquo;s initial selection of them makes it more costly for the commission to negatively evaluate them upon retention. We provide evidence leveraging the Article 255 panel for (re)appointments to the Court of Justice of the European Union.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;published-work&#34;&gt;Published work&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If who makes decisions within courts matters for the outcome of cases and their reception, then studying how cases and judges are matched is essential to understanding judicial independence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://siljehermansen.github.io/publication/jlc2023/&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;The CJEU Database Platform: Decisions and Decision-Makers&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;  (2023)  with Stein Arne Brekke, Joshua Fjelstul and Daniel Naurin. &lt;em&gt;Journal of Law and Courts&lt;/em&gt; 0(0), 1-22.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://siljehermansen.github.io/publication/jepp2020/&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Building legitimacy: strategic case allocations in the Court of Justice of the European Union&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;  (2020) &lt;em&gt;Journal of European Public Policy&lt;/em&gt; 27 (8), 1215-1235.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Building legitimacy: strategic case allocations in the Court of Justice of the European Union</title>
      <link>https://siljehermansen.github.io/publication/jepp2020/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://siljehermansen.github.io/publication/jepp2020/</guid>
      <description>&lt;!---
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;MarginalEffect_First_B_item_Current_government_-_weighted0.jpeg&#34; width=&#34;50%&#34; align=&#34;left&#34; alt=&#34;No effect of government preferences in non-politicized cases.&#34;/&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;MarginalEffect_First_B_item_Current_government_-_weighted1.jpeg&#34; width=&#34;50%&#34; align=&#34;right&#34; alt=&#34;Effect of government preferences in politicized cases. Author: Silje Synnøve Lyder Hermansen.&#34;/&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;small&gt;Figure: Judges whose governments hold outlying economic preferences are less likely to act as rapporteur in court cases that could divide member states.&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
---&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;NotDebatedLegislation.jpeg&#34; width=&#34;50%&#34; align=&#34;left&#34; alt=&#34;No effect of government preferences in non-politicized cases.&#34;/&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;DebatedLegislation.jpeg&#34; width=&#34;50%&#34; align=&#34;right&#34; alt=&#34;Effect of government preferences in politicized cases. Author: Silje Synnøve Lyder Hermansen.&#34;/&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;small&gt;Figure: Judges whose governments hold outlying economic preferences are less likely to act as rapporteur in court cases that could divide member states.&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Abstract&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Does the President of the Court of Justice of the European Union (CJEU) make strategic use of his members?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cases in the CJEU areprepared  by  a  “judge-rapporteur”  who  acts  as  an  agenda  setter. I argue that the President builds the Court’s legitimacy by strategically allocating cases to select judges.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Using original data on 9623 case allocations (1980-2015), I argue that suspicions about judges’ political accountability can polarize already politicized debates.  The President circumvents such dynamicsby  appointing  a  rapporteur  whose  government  holds  moderate  political  preferences.   However,  he  considers  governmental  preferencesand disagreements mainly when case law is not yet developed.  This may  also  contribute  to  explaining  judges individual-level  specialization, which arguably favors the construction of a coherent case law.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The results speak to the lingering effect of judges’ renewable terms &amp;ndash; despite secret voting &amp;ndash; as well as the importance of courts internalorganization for judicial independence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Reference&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Hermansen, Silje Synnøve Lyder (2020) &lt;a href=&#34;http://dx.doi.org/10.1080/13501763.2020.1714697&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Building legitimacy: strategic case allocations in the Court of Justice of the European Union&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt; &lt;em&gt;Journal of European Public Policy&lt;/em&gt;, 27(8), pp 1215-1235&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
