<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Judicial behavior on Silje Synnøve Lyder Hermansen</title>
    <link>/tags/judicial-behavior/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Judicial behavior on Silje Synnøve Lyder Hermansen</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 01 Aug 2019 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	    <atom:link href="/tags/judicial-behavior/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Decision makers in the Court of Justice of the European Union (CJEU)</title>
      <link>/project/court-of-justice-of-the-european-union/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Aug 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/project/court-of-justice-of-the-european-union/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;The Court of Justice of the European Union (CJEU) has established itself as the world’s most influential international court, functioning in many respects as a federal supreme court.  This project aims to better understand the conditions for -– and therefore the limits of -– the Court’s independence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I open the black box of the decision-making process to consider governments’ and judges’ individual behavior. As of today, very little research exists on how judges enter the Court and how its internal organization affect decision-making.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!---## [Case allocation within the Court](case-allocation)---&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;case-allocation-within-the-court&#34;&gt;Case allocation within the Court&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;!---* &lt;a href=&#34;TendingTheBar_Hermansen.pdf&#34; style=&#34;color: #000000&#34;&gt;**&#34;Tending the Bar: Strategic Case Allocations in
the Court of Justice of the European Union&#34;**&lt;/a&gt;   presented at EPSA Annual Meeting 2019 (Belfast)---&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&amp;ldquo;Tending the Bar: Strategic Case Allocations in the Court of Justice of the European Union&amp;rdquo;&lt;/strong&gt; presented at EPSA Annual Meeting 2019 (Belfast)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Does the President of the Court of Justice of the European Union (CJEU) make strategic use of his members? To date, studies in the separation-of-powers tradition have considered the Court’s behavior at the organizational level. In contrast, this paper focuses on the effect of external strategic considerations on allocation of influence within the Court.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Contrary to many other international courts, influence in the CJEU is individualized and distributed at the discretion of its leadership. First, I show that the President promotes individual-level specialization and argue that this favors consistency in the Court’s output. Second, I argue that suspicions about judges’ political accountability can polarize already politicized cases. The President shortcuts such dynamics by allocating cases to judges whose governments occupy a moderate position.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I rely on original data on allocations in 9955 cases brought before the CJEU (1980-2015). The results speak to the role of internal organization for judicial independence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;MarginalEffect_First_B_item_Current_government_-_weighted0.jpeg&#34; width=&#34;50%&#34; align=&#34;left&#34; alt=&#34;No effect of government preferences in non-politicized cases.&#34;/&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;MarginalEffect_First_B_item_Current_government_-_weighted1.jpeg&#34; width=&#34;50%&#34; align=&#34;right&#34; alt=&#34;Effect of government preferences in politicized cases.&#34;/&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Judges from member states with outlying economic preferences are less likely to act as rapporteur in cases dividing goverments.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A draft version can be found &lt;a href=&#34;TendingTheBar_Hermansen.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;appointment-of-judges&#34;&gt;Appointment of judges&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&amp;ldquo;Will do? Selecting Judges on the Basis of Policy Preferences or Performance Indicators&amp;rdquo;&lt;/strong&gt;  with Daniel Naurin presented at the ECPR Joint Sessions 2019 (Mons)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;!---* &lt;a href=&#34;WillDo_HermansenNaurin.pdf&#34; style=&#34;color: #000000&#34;&gt;**&#34;Will do? Selecting Judges on the Basis of Policy Preferences or Performance Indicators&#34;**&lt;/a&gt;  with Daniel Naurin presented at the ECPR Joint Sessions 2019 (Mons)---&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Are governments’ appointments of judges to the Court of Justice of the European Union (CJEU) politicized? And does this prevent them for emphasizing competence? The power to select judges is key to representative institutions’ control over the judiciary. Nevertheless, while the CJEU is the most powerful of international courts and motor of the judicialization of politics in Europe, the selection criteria that governments follow have remained a blank in the literature.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Judges in the CJEU sit for six years renewable. All cases are decided collectively and in secrecy, so the policies judges favor are unknown. However, their influence &amp;ndash; in terms of the positions they obtain –&amp;ndash; is known. We therefore start by assuming that judges are selected for their preferences, but sanctioned for their performance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;Effect_of_preferences_on_change_of_judge.jpeg&#34; width=&#34;50%&#34; align=&#34;right&#34;/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We rely on original data on all potential reappointment decisions to the CJEU over a 60-year period, biographical information and key performance measures of judges’ activities at the Court.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We find on the one hand that governments with different economic preferences hold different preferences over judges. That is, a change in government preferences increases the likelihood of changing the sitting judge. On the other hand, we find that governments &amp;ndash; regardless of their political preferences &amp;ndash; are more likely to retain judges who have obtained positions of influence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A draft version can be found &lt;a href=&#34;WillDo_HermansenNaurin.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!---
## Data collection on decision makers
The internal organization of the Court has become both more complex and more hierarchical over time.
![The internal organization of the Court has become both more complex and more hierarchical over time.](Timeline.gif)
---&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
