<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Silje Synnøve Lyder Hermansen</title>
    <link>/authors/admin/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Silje Synnøve Lyder Hermansen</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 20 Nov 2019 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	    <atom:link href="/authors/admin/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Decision makers in the Court of Justice of the European Union (CJEU)</title>
      <link>/project/court-of-justice-of-the-european-union/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 20 Nov 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/project/court-of-justice-of-the-european-union/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;The Court of Justice of the European Union (CJEU) is probably the world’s most influential international court, functioning in many respects as a federal supreme court.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As of today, little research exists on how judges enter the Court and how its internal organization affect decision making.  This project opens the black box of these decision-making processes to consider governments’ and judges’ strategic behavior.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I show that judges&amp;rsquo; performance and governments&amp;rsquo; political preferences are intertwined both when judges are appointed and when cases are allocated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!---## [Case allocation within the Court](case-allocation)---&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;case-allocation-within-the-cjeu&#34;&gt;Case allocation within the CJEU&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;!---* &lt;a href=&#34;TendingTheBar_Hermansen.pdf&#34; style=&#34;color: #000000&#34;&gt;**&#34;Tending the Bar: Strategic Case Allocations in
the Court of Justice of the European Union&#34;**&lt;/a&gt;   presented at EPSA Annual Meeting 2019 (Belfast)---&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If who makes decisions within courts matters for the outcome of cases and their reception, then studying how cases and judges are matched is essential to understanding judicial independence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&amp;ldquo;Building Legitimacy: Strategic Case Allocations in the Court of Justice of the European Union&amp;rdquo;&lt;/strong&gt; presented at EPSA Annual Meeting 2019 (Belfast)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Does the President of the Court of Justice of the European Union (CJEU) make strategic use of his members? Despite its considerable independence, the Court demonstrates substantial self-restraint when confronted with member states&amp;rsquo; preferences. However, to date, studies in the separation-of-powers tradition have considered judicial behavior at the organizational level. In contrast, this paper focuses on how external strategic considerations translate to individual influence &lt;em&gt;within&lt;/em&gt; the CJEU.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Influence in the Court is individualized and distributed at the leadership&amp;rsquo;s discretion. All cases are prepared by a ``judge-rapporteur&amp;rdquo; who acts as an agenda setter. This study argues that the President seeks to build the Court&amp;rsquo;s legitimacy by strategically allocating cases to select judges. I show that individual-level specialization is promoted and argue that it favors a consistent case law. I then argue that suspicions about judges&amp;rsquo; political accountability can polarize already politicized cases. The President shortcuts such dynamics by allocating cases to judges whose governments hold moderate political preferences.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I rely on original data on 9623 case allocations in CJEU (1980-2015). The results speak to the lingering effect of judges&amp;rsquo; renewable terms &amp;ndash; despite secret voting &amp;ndash; as well as the importance of an autonomous internal organization for judicial independence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;MarginalEffect_First_B_item_Current_government_-_weighted0.jpeg&#34; width=&#34;50%&#34; align=&#34;left&#34; alt=&#34;No effect of government preferences in non-politicized cases.&#34;/&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;MarginalEffect_First_B_item_Current_government_-_weighted1.jpeg&#34; width=&#34;50%&#34; align=&#34;right&#34; alt=&#34;Effect of government preferences in politicized cases.&#34;/&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Judges whose governments hold outlying economic preferences are less likely to act as rapporteur in court cases that could divide member states.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A draft version can be found &lt;a href=&#34;BuildingLegitimacy_Hermansen.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;judicial-appointments-to-the-cjeu&#34;&gt;Judicial appointments to the CJEU&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&amp;ldquo;Will do? Selecting Judges on the Basis of Policy Preferences or Performance Indicators&amp;rdquo;&lt;/strong&gt;  with Daniel Naurin presented at the ECPR Joint Sessions 2019 (Mons)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;!---* &lt;a href=&#34;WillDo_HermansenNaurin.pdf&#34; style=&#34;color: #000000&#34;&gt;**&#34;Will do? Selecting Judges on the Basis of Policy Preferences or Performance Indicators&#34;**&lt;/a&gt;  with Daniel Naurin presented at the ECPR Joint Sessions 2019 (Mons)---&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Are governments’ appointments of judges to the Court of Justice of the European Union (CJEU) politicized? And does this prevent them for emphasizing competence? The power to select judges is key to representative institutions’ control over the judiciary. Nevertheless, while the CJEU is the most powerful of international courts and motor of the judicialization of politics in Europe, the selection criteria for judicial appointments have remained a blank in the literature.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Judges in the CJEU sit for six years renewable. All cases are decided collectively and in secrecy, so the policies judges favor are unknown. However, their influence &amp;ndash; in terms of the positions they obtain –&amp;ndash; is known. We therefore start by assuming that judges are selected for their preferences, but sanctioned for their performance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;Effect_of_preferences_on_change_of_judge.jpeg&#34; width=&#34;50%&#34; align=&#34;right&#34; alt=&#34;Graphic showing that the likelihood of replacing a sitting judge increases with the distance between the economic preferences of the appointing and reappointing government.&#34;/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We rely on original data on all potential reappointment decisions to the CJEU over a 60-year period, biographical information and key performance measures of judges’ activities at the Court.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We find on the one hand that governments with different economic preferences hold different preferences over judges. That is, a change in government preferences increases the likelihood of changing the sitting judge. On the other hand, we find that governments &amp;ndash; regardless of their political preferences &amp;ndash; are more likely to retain judges who have obtained positions of influence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A draft version can be found &lt;a href=&#34;WillDo_HermansenNaurin.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;judicial-decision-making&#34;&gt;Judicial decision-making&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Measuring the evolution of CJEU case law using word embeddings&lt;/strong&gt; presented at Big Insight - a center for research-based innovation, Norwegian Computing Center. 2019.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To study the conditions for judicial activism – self-restraint, initiation or expansion of case law – we need a consistent and comparable measure of court output. Can machine learning help us in this respect? This research note discusses ways of comparing court documents in order to obtain such measures. The focus is on word embeddings, which allow researchers to identify similar – but not identical – terms and use them as building blocks for document-level comparisons.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;Effect_of_judgment_similarity_on_academic_attention.png&#34; width=&#34;50%&#34; align=&#34;left&#34; alt=&#34;Effect of judgment similarity on academic attention (annotations in legal journals).&#34;/&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Analyzing the evolution of case law requires researchers to read and compare judgments. It is a resource-intensive process both in terms of competence and number of working hours. Assessing the outcome of a case typically requires familiarity with legal precedent in the court, the doctrines under- pinning rulings as well at the type of cases brought before the tribunal. In other words, - depending on the task – the researcher needs a good grasp of similar cases in the past (i.e. legal precedent) and/or the future (i.e. its value as a precedent) as well as the field-specific vocabulary.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The purpose of this research note is to train a model to make such comparisons for us. To obtain word embeddings, I apply a word2vec algorithm on 30999 (machine-readable) legal texts produced by the members of the Court of Justice of the European Union (CJEU) itself. I use these to construct a do- main specific vocabulary of similar words. The similarities can then be used to identify and compare relevant documents based on their word occurrences.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A draft version can be found &lt;a href=&#34;WordEmbeddings_Hermansen.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!---
## Data collection on decision makers
The internal organization of the Court has become both more complex and more hierarchical over time.
![The internal organization of the Court has become both more complex and more hierarchical over time.](Timeline.gif)
---&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Statistical analysis (STV4020B)</title>
      <link>/teaching/stv4020b/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 15 Nov 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/teaching/stv4020b/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;Master&amp;rsquo;s/PhD level. &lt;em&gt;University of Oslo. Department of Political Science.&lt;/em&gt; 2019&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;course-description&#34;&gt;Course description&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This course provides a toolkit for students looking to execute their own research projects using quantitative methods. We go through the statistical theory behind models, but we emphasize understanding when models are useful and how to employ them. The course helps students 1) identify appropriate statistical models that describe different data types and 2) design studies that enable causal inference (as opposed to merely establishing correlation).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many of the phenomena political scientists take interest in can be classified into categories or events. This includes variables like voters&amp;rsquo; choice of party, number of violent incidences in a time span or time between violent events. The course introduces students to a number of models which are specifically designed to describe the underlying phenomenon that generates such data. The focus of the first part of the course is on correlations. Our purpose is to help students gear the statistical analysis towards a realistic description of the data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Beyond statistical description, researchers&amp;rsquo; interest in political phenomena is often motivated by a wish to identify their causes. Causal claims focus on whether we would continue to observe $y$ even in the absence of $x$. This is a typical question when studying the effect of policies, for example. The potential outcomes framework provides a useful heuristic for assessing causal relationships.  The second part of the course is devoted to a set of quantitative research designs that can be used to make causal inferences.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Learning outcome&lt;/strong&gt; Students will get hands-on practice by learning how to implement the various techniques and by replicating existing studies in R. Students will also learn how to present results in a manner that is understandable to a general audience, for example by using graphs and other visual tools.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;More information&lt;/strong&gt; about the course is available at the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.uio.no/studier/emner/sv/statsvitenskap/STV4020B/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;University of Oslo&amp;rsquo;s webpages&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div&gt;
&lt;object data=&#34;syllabus_stv4020b&#34; type=&#34;application/pdf&#34; width=&#34;700&#34; height=&#34;950&#34;&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;syllabus.pdf&#34;&gt;Download the syllabus&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/object&gt;
&lt;/div&gt; 

&lt;h3 id=&#34;slides&#34;&gt;Slides&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Maximum likelihood&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;Lecture2_Logit.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Logistic regression&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; (Ward and Ahlquist, 2018, ch 3)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Logistic regression is the base-line example of a generalized linear model (GLM).
We go through how to model binary outcomes, how to interpret the results from a logit and why we can&amp;rsquo;t simply run an OLS.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;Lecture3_Choice.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Ordered and multinomial regression&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; (Ward and Ahlquist, 2018, ch 8-9)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We go through models with categorical dependent variables: Ordinal and nominal categories. Example data used in class can be downloaded &lt;a href=&#34;kap10.txt&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. It is the same as the data from chapter 10 in laerdegR.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;LaTeX.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;LaTeX + R = Sant&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A brief introduction to LaTeX and how to use it in combination with R scripts (in Norwegian).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!---## Flexibility
This feature can be used for publishing content such as:

* **Online courses**
* **Project or software documentation**
* **Tutorials**

The `courses` folder may be renamed. For example, we can rename it to `docs` for software/project documentation or `tutorials` for creating an online course.

## Delete tutorials

**To remove these pages, delete the `courses` folder and see below to delete the associated menu link.**

## Update site menu

After renaming or deleting the `courses` folder, you may wish to update any `[[main]]` menu links to it by editing your menu configuration at `config/_default/menus.toml`.

For example, if you delete this folder, you can remove the following from your menu configuration:

```toml
[[main]]
  name = &#34;Courses&#34;
  url = &#34;courses/&#34;
  weight = 50
```

Or, if you are creating a software documentation site, you can rename the `courses` folder to `docs` and update the associated *Courses* menu configuration to:

```toml
[[main]]
  name = &#34;Docs&#34;
  url = &#34;docs/&#34;
  weight = 50
```

## Update the docs menu

If you use the *docs* layout, note that the name of the menu in the front matter should be in the form `[menu.X]` where `X` is the folder name. Hence, if you rename the `courses/example/` folder, you should also rename the menu definitions in the front matter of files within `courses/example/` from `[menu.example]` to `[menu.&lt;NewFolderName&gt;]`.
---&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Installere R-pakken</title>
      <link>/data/laerdegr/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Aug 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/data/laerdegr/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.fagbokforlaget.no/L%C3%A6r-deg-R/I9788245022131&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Lær deg R&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt; er en innføringsbok i statistikkprogrammet R utgitt av Fagbokforlaget (2019). Boka er levert med datasett, øvelsesoppgaver og løsningsforslag, slik at du kan prøve deg på egen hånd. Her kan du laste ned denne nettressursen. Den kommer som en egen R-pakke.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pakken kan installeres fra lokal fil eller rett fra GitHub.
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.fagbokforlaget.no/L%C3%A6r-deg-R/I9788245022131&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;laerdegr.jpg&#34; width=&#34;35%&#34; align=&#34;right&#34; alt=&#34;Lær deg R: En innføring i statistikkprogrammets muligheter. Forfatter: Silje Synnøve Lyder Hermansen&#34;&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;installere-fra-lokal-fil&#34;&gt;Installere fra lokal fil&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Denne løsningen gjøres i to skritt.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;På denne siden&lt;/strong&gt; laster du ned pakken ved å trykke på én av disse lenkene:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For alle operativsystemer:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/SiljeHermansen/laerdegR/raw/master/laerdegR_0.1.0.tar.gz&#34; download&gt;
&lt;button class=&#34;button&#34;&gt;&lt;i class=&#34;fa fa-download&#34;&gt;&lt;/i&gt; laerdegR_0.1.0.tar.gz&lt;/button&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Windows-brukere kan også benytte seg av denne:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/SiljeHermansen/laerdegR/raw/master/laerdegR_0.1.0.zip&#34; download&gt;
&lt;button class=&#34;button&#34;&gt;&lt;i class=&#34;fa fa-download&#34;&gt;&lt;/i&gt; laerdegR_0.1.0.zip&lt;/button&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Filen vil da lastes ned på din maskin. Om du ikke har spesifisert annet, vil den ligge i mappen som kalles &amp;ldquo;Downloads&amp;rdquo; på maskinen din.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;I RStudio&lt;/strong&gt; installerer du filen i R-biblioteket.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Klikk på fanen som kalles &amp;ldquo;Packages&amp;rdquo; i vinduet nederst til høyre.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Klikk så på &amp;ldquo;Install&amp;rdquo;. I kommunikasjonsvinduet som så åpner seg, skal du velge &amp;ldquo;Install from: Package Archive File&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Under &amp;ldquo;Package archive:&amp;rdquo; må du deretter klikke på &amp;ldquo;Browse&amp;rdquo; og navigere deg fram til filen du nettopp lastet ned.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Klikk så på &amp;ldquo;Install&amp;rdquo;. Nå skrives installasjonskommandoen til R, og R skal i rask rekkefølge gi deg beskjed i rød skrift om at pakken installeres, og i svart skrift at &lt;code&gt;package ‘laerdegR’ successfully unpacked and MD5 sums checked&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Om møter på feilmeldinger, bør du sjekke at tilleggsargumentene i installasjonskoden er korrekte. Filadressa (&lt;code&gt;C:/Downloads/&lt;/code&gt;) vil åpenbart variere fra maskin til maskin.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Om du har valgt tar.gz-fil, må koden se slik ut.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;install.packages(&amp;quot;C:/Downloads/laerdegR_0.1.0.tar.gz&amp;quot;, repos = NULL, type = &amp;quot;source&amp;quot;)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Om du har valgt zip-fil, må koden se slik ut.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;install.packages(&amp;quot;C:/Downloads/laerdegR_0.1.0.zip&amp;quot;, repos = NULL, type = &amp;quot;binary&amp;quot;)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;installere-direkte-fra-github&#34;&gt;Installere direkte fra GitHub&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Denne løsningen krever mer manøvrering.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;I nettleseren:&lt;/strong&gt; Begynn med å laste ned og installere &lt;a href=&#34;https://cran.r-project.org/bin/windows/Rtools/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;RTools&lt;/a&gt; uten å åpne RStudio.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;I RStudio:&lt;/strong&gt; installere &lt;code&gt;devtools&lt;/code&gt;-pakken og hent den inn fra biblioteket.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;install.packages(&#39;devtools&#39;)
library(devtools)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nå kan du laste ned og installere nettressursen direkte fra GitHubs sider.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;install_github(&amp;quot;SiljeHermansen/laerdegR&amp;quot;)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Lær deg R</title>
      <link>/publication/laerdegr/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Aug 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/publication/laerdegr/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.fagbokforlaget.no/L%C3%A6r-deg-R/I9788245022131&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;laerdegr.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Lær deg R: En innføring i statistikkprogrammets muligheter. Forfatter: Silje Synnøve Lyder Hermansen&#34;&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Abstract&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt; Velkommen til R-universet! Lær deg R er introduksjonen for deg som ønsker et godt arbeidsverktøy for statistisk analyse.  R har vokst enormt i popularitet de siste årene, og med god grunn. R er gratis og dekker analysebehovene til nybegynnere så vel som eksperter.&lt;/p&gt;  

&lt;p&gt;Boka er skrevet for samfunnsviteren som tar sine første skritt innen kvantitativ metode. Statistikk er et håndverk mer enn en vitenskap. Derfor er verktøyet viktig. Vi jobber sammen i RStudio, og går gjennom analysestadiene skritt for skritt. Vi laster inn data, tilrettelegger dem, gjør foranalyser og regresjonsanalyser. Fokuset er på å forstå hva som skjer, og kommunisere resultatene.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Boka er levert med datasett, øvelsesoppgaver og løsningsforslag, slik at du kan prøve deg på egen hånd. Alt du trenger er en datamaskin, internett og denne boka.&lt;/p&gt;
  

&lt;h3 id=&#34;lær-deg-r-pakken&#34;&gt;Lær deg R-pakken&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lær deg R-pakken er en nettressurs som gir deg tilgang til datasett og oppgaveløsninger som hører til boka. Du kan laste ned pakken som .tar.gz-fil eller som .zip-fil:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/SiljeHermansen/laerdegR/raw/master/laerdegR_0.1.0.tar.gz&#34; download&gt;
&lt;button class=&#34;button&#34;&gt;&lt;i class=&#34;fa fa-download&#34;&gt;&lt;/i&gt; laerdegR_0.1.0.tar.gz&lt;/button&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/SiljeHermansen/laerdegR/raw/master/laerdegR_0.1.0.zip&#34; download&gt;
&lt;button class=&#34;button&#34;&gt;&lt;i class=&#34;fa fa-download&#34;&gt;&lt;/i&gt; laerdegR_0.1.0.zip&lt;/button&gt;
&lt;/a&gt; 
&lt;/div&gt;
 

&lt;p&gt;Instrukser om hvordan du installerer pakken finner du på denne siden:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://siljehermansen.github.io/data/laerdegr&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Last ned og installere laerdegR&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;innholdsfortegnelse&#34;&gt;Innholdsfortegnelse&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Boka tar deg skritt for skritt gjennom en typisk forskningsprosess.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Vi begynner med å laste inn og tilrettelegge data, før vi går videre med beskrivende analyser. I siste del av boka kjører vi så regresjonsanalyser: OLS og logistisk regresjon. Vi har fokus på å forstå og tolke resultatene. Dette inkluderer også å vurdere modellens troverdighet gjennom ulike former for modellstatistikk.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div&gt;
&lt;object data=&#34;Innholdsfortegnelse.pdf&#34; type=&#34;application/pdf&#34; width=&#34;700&#34; height=&#34;950&#34;&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;Innholdsfortegnelse.pdf&#34;&gt;Innholdsfortegnelsen til Lær deg R (2019)&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/object&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;!---&lt;embed src=&#34;Innholdsfortegnelse.pdf&#34; width=&#34;700&#34; height=&#34;950&#34; alt=&#34;Innholdsfortegnelse til Lær deg R&#34; pluginspage=&#34;http://www.adobe.com/products/acrobat/readstep2.html&#34;&gt;
---&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Reference&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Hermansen, Silje Synnøve Lyder (2019) &lt;a href=&#34;Innhold_bibliografi.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Lær deg R: En innføring i statistikkprogrammets muligheter&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, Bergen: Fagbokforlaget.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Striving for influence: The effect of performance on candidate selection</title>
      <link>/publication/pp2018/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Jul 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/publication/pp2018/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://journals.sagepub.com/doi/full/10.1177/1354068816663036&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;reselection_performance.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Effect of signals of performance on incumbent candidate selection to the European Parliament. Author: Silje Hermansen.&#34;&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Abstract&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I consider how asymmetric information between the party selectorate and members of Parliament affects the renomination of incumbent candidates. By applying an adverse selection model, I argue that the selectorate looks to past performance to select candidates it expects will gain influence. However, the impact of performance varies according to the need for and availability of information.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The European Parliament (EP) provides a most-likely case for information asymmetry. Studying three elections in 11 member states, I find that the allocation of influential positions in office improves chances of reselection. The effect increases when the allocation is more selective, and when the prior uncertainty around candidacies is high. The study thus proposes a new approach to the relationship between national parties and transnational groups in the EP. It also suggests venues for research on parliamentary politics and candidate selection in general. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Replication files&lt;/strong&gt; can be downloaded &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/SiljeHermansen/Replication-files&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Reference&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Hermansen, Silje Synnøve Lyder (2018) &amp;ldquo;Striving for influence: The effect of performance on candidate selection&amp;rdquo; &lt;em&gt;Party Politics&lt;/em&gt; 24 (4), 382-396.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>(Self-)selection and expertise among decision-makers in the European Parliament</title>
      <link>/publication/jls2018/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 16 Mar 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/publication/jls2018/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.tandfonline.com/doi/full/10.1080/13572334.2018.1444631&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;coefplot_expertise.png&#34; alt=&#34;Coefplot reporting effect of policy expertise on allocation of codecision reports. Author: Silje Hermansen.&#34;&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Abstract&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rapporteurs in the European Parliament (EP) are the most influential members in terms of the legislation they handle. They are appointed by their political groups. In making these appointments, these groups need to accommodate both their collective needs and individual requests.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This article explores situations in which the collective need for information is prioritised: the codecision procedure. The data includes allocations over a 10-year period (2004–2014) in three of the most powerful EP committees, as well as key career choices among members.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;EP groups emphasise policy-specific expertise. They also pay attention to individual members’ requests for exposure, but only when the expected policy drift is minimal. Harsh selection during the allocation of codecision reports creates pressure to accommodate a greater selection of legislators during other attractive report allocations. Own-initiative reports therefore affect allocation of codecision reports negatively.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Online supplementary files&lt;/strong&gt; can be downloaded &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/SiljeHermansen/Replication-files&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Reference&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Hermansen, Silje Synnøve Lyder (2018) &amp;ldquo;(Self-)selection and expertise among decision-makers in the European Parliament&amp;rdquo;, &lt;em&gt;The Journal of Legislative Studies&lt;/em&gt;, 24 (1), pp 148-172.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Choosing Agents: Members of the European Parliament and their Political Organizations Seen through Report Allocation</title>
      <link>/publication/phd2017/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 10 Mar 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/publication/phd2017/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.duo.uio.no/bitstream/handle/10852/69004/PhD-LyderHermansen-2017.pdf?sequence=4&amp;isAllowed=y&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;committee_activity.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Graphic illustrating the variation in committee activity in the European Parliament (1999-2014). Author: Silje Synnøve Lyder Hermansen&#34;&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Abstract&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This dissertation treats with partisan organization in the European Parliament (EP) and its impact on members’ (MEPs) career opportunities. National parties organize elections. Parliamentary work is organized around transnational political groups. They do not share any overarching organizational structure. My contributions pertain to the interconnected choices made by MEPs and their two party organizations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Parliamentary groups face a trade-off between the need for expertise and the risk of agency drift. Groups allocate reports to maximize the value added by the rapporteur while limiting the drift. They prefer policy experts to generalists and -- up to a point -- experienced MEPs to newcomers. Groups also balance individual demands with the collective need.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;National parties do not have institutionalized presence in the EP. They enter into an outcome-based contract similar to voters. MEPs are either rewarded by reselection or kicked out of office. Report alloca-tions dissipate uncertainty about MEPs’ ability. They thus improve MEPs’ career prospects to the extent that parties need new information about agent quality, and to the extent that parliamentary groups can provide it.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
