<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>R on Silje Synnøve Lyder Hermansen</title>
    <link>/tags/r/</link>
    <description>Recent content in R on Silje Synnøve Lyder Hermansen</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 26 Aug 2019 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	    <atom:link href="/tags/r/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Statistical analysis (STV4020B)</title>
      <link>/teaching/stv4020b/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 26 Aug 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/teaching/stv4020b/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Master&amp;rsquo;s/PhD level. &lt;em&gt;University of Oslo. Department of Political Science.&lt;/em&gt; 2019&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This course provides a toolkit for students looking to execute their own research projects using quantitative methods. We go through the statistical theory behind models, but we emphasize understanding when models are useful and how to employ them. The course helps students 1) identify appropriate statistical models that describe different data types and 2) design studies that enable causal inference (as opposed to merely establishing correlation).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many of the phenomena political scientists take interest in can be classified into categories or events. This includes variables like voters&amp;rsquo; choice of party, number of violent incidences in a time span or time between violent events. The course introduces students to a number of models which are specifically designed to describe the underlying phenomenon that generates such data. The focus of the first part of the course is on correlations. Our purpose is to help students gear the statistical analysis towards a realistic description of the data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Beyond statistical description, researchers&amp;rsquo; interest in political phenomena is often motivated by a wish to identify their causes. Causal claims focus on whether we would continue to observe $y$ even in the absence of $x$. This is a typical question when studying the effect of policies, for example. The potential outcomes framework provides a useful heuristic for assessing causal relationships.  The second part of the course is devoted to a set of quantitative research designs that can be used to make causal inferences.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Learning outcome&lt;/strong&gt; Students will get hands-on practice by learning how to implement the various techniques and by replicating existing studies in R. Students will also learn how to present results in a manner that is understandable to a general audience, for example by using graphs and other visual tools.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;More information&lt;/strong&gt; about the course is available at the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.uio.no/studier/emner/sv/statsvitenskap/STV4020B/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;University of Oslo&amp;rsquo;s webpages&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div&gt;
&lt;object data=&#34;syllabus.pdf&#34; type=&#34;application/pdf&#34; width=&#34;700&#34; height=&#34;950&#34;&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;syllabus.pdf&#34;&gt;Download the syllabus&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/object&gt;
&lt;/div&gt; 

&lt;!---## Flexibility
This feature can be used for publishing content such as:

* **Online courses**
* **Project or software documentation**
* **Tutorials**

The `courses` folder may be renamed. For example, we can rename it to `docs` for software/project documentation or `tutorials` for creating an online course.

## Delete tutorials

**To remove these pages, delete the `courses` folder and see below to delete the associated menu link.**

## Update site menu

After renaming or deleting the `courses` folder, you may wish to update any `[[main]]` menu links to it by editing your menu configuration at `config/_default/menus.toml`.

For example, if you delete this folder, you can remove the following from your menu configuration:

```toml
[[main]]
  name = &#34;Courses&#34;
  url = &#34;courses/&#34;
  weight = 50
```

Or, if you are creating a software documentation site, you can rename the `courses` folder to `docs` and update the associated *Courses* menu configuration to:

```toml
[[main]]
  name = &#34;Docs&#34;
  url = &#34;docs/&#34;
  weight = 50
```

## Update the docs menu

If you use the *docs* layout, note that the name of the menu in the front matter should be in the form `[menu.X]` where `X` is the folder name. Hence, if you rename the `courses/example/` folder, you should also rename the menu definitions in the front matter of files within `courses/example/` from `[menu.example]` to `[menu.&lt;NewFolderName&gt;]`.
---&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Lær deg R</title>
      <link>/publication/laerdegr/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Aug 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/publication/laerdegr/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.fagbokforlaget.no/L%C3%A6r-deg-R/I9788245022131&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;laerdegr.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Lær deg R: En innføring i statistikkprogrammets muligheter. Forfatter: Silje Synnøve Lyder Hermansen&#34;&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Abstract&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt; Velkommen til R-universet! Lær deg R er introduksjonen for deg som ønsker et godt arbeidsverktøy for statistisk analyse.  R har vokst enormt i popularitet de siste årene, og med god grunn. R er gratis og dekker analysebehovene til nybegynnere så vel som eksperter.&lt;/p&gt;  
    &lt;p&gt;Boka er skrevet for samfunnsviteren som tar sine første skritt innen kvantitativ metode. Statistikk er et håndverk mer enn en vitenskap. Derfor er verktøyet viktig. Vi jobber sammen i RStudio, og går gjennom analysestadiene skritt for skritt. Vi laster inn data, tilrettelegger dem, gjør foranalyser og regresjonsanalyser. Fokuset er på å forstå hva som skjer, og kommunisere resultatene.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Boka er levert med datasett, øvelsesoppgaver og løsningsforslag, slik at du kan prøve deg på egen hånd. Alt du trenger er en datamaskin, internett og denne boka.&lt;/p&gt;
  

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Lær deg R-pakken&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lær deg R-pakken er en nettressurs som gir deg tilgang til datasett og oppgaveløsninger som hører til boka. Du kan laste ned pakken som .tar.gz-fil eller som .zip-fil:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/SiljeHermansen/laerdegR/raw/master/laerdegR_0.1.0.tar.gz&#34; download&gt;
&lt;button class=&#34;button&#34;&gt;&lt;i class=&#34;fa fa-download&#34;&gt;&lt;/i&gt; laerdegR_0.1.0.tar.gz&lt;/button&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/SiljeHermansen/laerdegR/raw/master/laerdegR_0.1.0.zip&#34; download&gt;
&lt;button class=&#34;button&#34;&gt;&lt;i class=&#34;fa fa-download&#34;&gt;&lt;/i&gt; laerdegR_0.1.0.zip&lt;/button&gt;
&lt;/a&gt; 
&lt;/div&gt;
 

&lt;p&gt;Instrukser om hvordan du installerer pakken finner du på denne siden:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://siljehermansen.github.io/data/laerdegr&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Last ned og installere laerdegR&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Innholdsfortegnelse&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Boka tar deg skritt for skritt gjennom en typisk forskningsprosess.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Vi begynner med å laste inn og tilrettelegge data, før vi går videre med beskrivende analyser. I siste del av boka kjører vi så regresjonsanalyser: OLS og logistisk regresjon. Vi har fokus på å forstå og tolke resultatene. Dette inkluderer også å vurdere modellens troverdighet gjennom ulike former for modellstatistikk.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div&gt;
&lt;object data=&#34;Innholdsfortegnelse.pdf&#34; type=&#34;application/pdf&#34; width=&#34;700&#34; height=&#34;950&#34;&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;Innholdsfortegnelse.pdf&#34;&gt;Innholdsfortegnelsen til Lær deg R (2019)&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/object&gt;
&lt;/div&gt; 

&lt;!---&lt;embed src=&#34;Innholdsfortegnelse.pdf&#34; width=&#34;700&#34; height=&#34;950&#34; alt=&#34;Innholdsfortegnelse til Lær deg R&#34; pluginspage=&#34;http://www.adobe.com/products/acrobat/readstep2.html&#34;&gt;
---&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Teaching</title>
      <link>/teaching/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/teaching/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;These pages are intended to provide supplementary information to students. For a comprehensive overview of my past teaching activities, please refer to my CV.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;a-href-stv4020b-statistical-analysis-stv4020b-a&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;stv4020b&#34;&gt;Statistical analysis (STV4020B)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Master&#39;s/PhD level. &lt;i&gt;University of Oslo. Department of Political Science.&lt;/i&gt; 2019&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Advanced statistical analysis for social scientists. We go through the fundamental principals of causal inference as well as the most common generalized linear models (GLMs). Course given together with Øyvind Stiansen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;a-href-sfs10207-samfunnsvitenskapelig-forskningsmetode-sfs10207-a&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;sfs10207&#34;&gt;Samfunnsvitenskapelig forskningsmetode  (SFS10207)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bachelor&#39;s level. &lt;i&gt;Østfold University College. Faculty of Business, Languages, and Social Sciences. &lt;/i&gt; 2013&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Introduction to research methods (Bachelor&#39;s level). Course given together with Mathias Johannessen.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
